<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A patterne of Christian loyaltie vvhereby any prudent man may clearely perceive, in what manner the new Oath of Allegiance, and every clause thereof, may in a true, and catholike sense, without danger of perjury, be taken by Roman Catholikes. And all the chiefe objections, which are usually made against the said Oath, either in particular, or in generall, may according to the grounds of Catholike religion bee easily answered. Collected out of authours, who have handled the whole matter more largely. By William Hovvard an English Catholike.</title>
            <author>Preston, Thomas, 1563-1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 150 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03751</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13871</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104244</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839983</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839983</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4449</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03751)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4449)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1177:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A patterne of Christian loyaltie vvhereby any prudent man may clearely perceive, in what manner the new Oath of Allegiance, and every clause thereof, may in a true, and catholike sense, without danger of perjury, be taken by Roman Catholikes. And all the chiefe objections, which are usually made against the said Oath, either in particular, or in generall, may according to the grounds of Catholike religion bee easily answered. Collected out of authours, who have handled the whole matter more largely. By William Hovvard an English Catholike.</title>
                  <author>Preston, Thomas, 1563-1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 61, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Badger,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>William Howard = Thomas Preston.</note>
                  <note>A defense of the 1606 Oath of Allegiance, whose use was being renewed at this time. A different text from Preston's 1616 defense.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A" in a woodcut frame.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oath of allegiance, 1606 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4449:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4449:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4449:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4449:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PATTERNE OF CHRISTIAN <hi>LOYALTIE:</hi> VVhereby any prudent man may clearely <hi>perceive, in what manner the</hi> New Oath <hi>of Allegiance,</hi> and every <hi>Clauſe</hi> thereof, may in a true, and <hi>Catholike</hi> ſenſe, without danger of <hi>Perjury,</hi> be taken by
<hi>Roman</hi> CATHOLIKES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> All the chiefe <hi>Objections,</hi> which are uſually made againſt the ſaid
<hi>Oath,</hi> either in <hi>particular,</hi> or in <hi>generall,</hi> may according to the grounds of <hi>Catholike</hi> Religion bee eaſily anſwered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Collected</hi> out of <hi>Authours,</hi> who have handled the whole matter more largely.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM HOVVARD an Engliſh <hi>Catholike.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Feare our <hi>Lord,</hi> my ſonne, and the <hi>King.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Proverbs <hi>24.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R.</hi> BADGER, 1634.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4449:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4449:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, THOMAS, <hi>Lord</hi> HOVVARD, <hi>Earle of</hi> Arundell and
<hi>Surrey,</hi> Primier Earle, and Earle Marſhall <hi>of England, Baron</hi> HOVVARD, Mowbray,
<hi>Segrave, Brus</hi> of <hi>Gower, Fitz-Alan, Clun,</hi> Oſwaldeſtre, Maltravers,
<hi>and</hi> Grayſtocke, <hi>Knight of the most Noble Order of the</hi> GARTER, <hi>and one of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties most Honourable Privie Councell.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>My very good</hi> LORD;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Titles on which this Dedication is grounded have prooved ſtronger then my baſhfulneſſe, or feare; for your ſingular candor of minde, makes mee hope an
<pb facs="tcp:4449:4"/>acceptance of my good intentions, though joyned with weake abillities, and (beſides the honour of my relation to your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> in bloud) the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience I have had of your Noble and gracious favour to my ſelfe in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, gives me aſſurance, that you will not bee diſpleaſed, if for protection in an undertaking expoſed to much op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, I addreſſe my ſelfe to your <hi>Lordſhip.</hi> For ſo earneſt have they been in this controverſy, as now at laſt (even ſince this little Treatiſe was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der preſſe) they have objected to me; that wee are bound to beleeve as mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of faith, the generalities delivered by the <hi>Popes Holineſſe,</hi> though the wiſedome (ſay they) of the See
<hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike</hi> for bearing to irritate Chriſtian <hi>Princes,</hi> deſcendes not to particulars.
<pb facs="tcp:4449:4"/>Thus indeavour they to beare us in hand, that wee are bound to profeſſe what they conceale from us, and that <hi>Catholike</hi> faith muſt bee all one with myſterie of
<hi>State,</hi> and conſequently every good <hi>Christian</hi> being bound to profeſſe his
<hi>faith,</hi> with the loſſe of his life and living, we muſt in this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bee tyed to no leſſe, for a ſecret in policie, thought fitting to bee kept from us out of reaſon of
<hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The very laying downe of this their laſt refuge, ſufficiently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covereth the weakeneſſe thereof: ſo it onely reſteth that I crave your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> pardon for preſenting it out of due place to your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4449:5"/>View; to whom as Chiefe, both by nature and merit, I am obliged to profeſſe my ſelfe,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>A faithfull and humble ſervant,</hi> WILLIAM HOVVARD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4449:5"/>
            <head>A PREMONITION to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is one thing <hi>(Courteous Reader)</hi> which I wiſh thee <hi>firſt</hi> of all to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, to wit, what great diſagreement there is among the learneder ſort of our
<hi>Engliſh Catholikes,</hi> by whom the leſſe learned are for the most part guided, in their opinions concerning the <hi>new Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance.</hi> For <hi>ſome</hi> condemne it for altogether unlawfull, nor to be taken with a ſafe conſcience by any good Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.
<hi>Others</hi> approve it for lawfull, and to containe nothing beſides a profeſsion of true
<hi>temporall</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, and therefore not to bee refuſed by any good Subject. A
<hi>third</hi> ſort there is, who carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>negatively,</hi> and in expreſſe words wil neither approve it, nor condemne it, but leave every man to his owne conſcience, which in very deed is to any ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious man, all circumſtances conſidered, a <hi>tacit</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving thereof.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who condemne it, are of <hi>two</hi> ſorts, the <hi>one</hi> extreamely violent, and are not afraid to taxe thoſe Catholikes who approve it, of flat <hi>hereſie,</hi> and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb facs="tcp:4449:6"/>them no true <hi>Catholikes,</hi> but rather <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes,</hi> falſly pretending, That the <hi>Popes</hi> power to <hi>depoſe Princes,</hi> is by all learned and good Catholikes a confeſſed and undoubted point of <hi>Catholike</hi> faith; That his power to
<hi>Excommunicate,</hi> and to <hi>abſolve</hi> from <hi>Oaths</hi> in generall is denied in the
<hi>Oath:</hi> And that the <hi>King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See theſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, nu 7.11.17.</note> and <hi>Parliament</hi> doe take upon them in this <hi>Oath</hi> the
<hi>Churches</hi> authority to <hi>define</hi> matters of <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Others</hi> there be who are not ſo violent, but much miſliking the former objections, they chiefly except againſt the <hi>Second,</hi> and <hi>Fourth</hi> Clauſe, how any man can truly ſweare, <hi>That the</hi> Pope <hi>hath not any power to depoſe the</hi> King,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſeeing that he hath at the leaſt a <hi>probable</hi> power to
<hi>depoſe</hi> him: and conſequently how any man can truly abjure, as <hi>dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi> and
<hi>hereticall</hi> this doctrine, and poſition, <hi>That Princes which be deprived by the</hi> Pope,<note place="margin">See theſe, and others anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, nu. 9.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>may be depoſed by their Subjects, or any other,</hi> ſeeing that it is at the least a
<hi>probable</hi> doctrine, it being approved by the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelfe, and by many other moſt learned Catholike <hi>Divines.</hi> And against the <hi>Oath</hi> in generall they urge, That our ſupreme <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall</hi> Paſtor hath forbidden it,<note place="margin">See theſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, nu. 26.32.39.</note> That to <hi>take</hi> it, is <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> and that to
<hi>refuſe</hi> it, is the <hi>ſafer way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when I perceived the beſt learned <hi>Prieſts</hi> of our Nation to diſagree ſo much in their opinions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this great, and dangerous controverſie of the <hi>Oath</hi> betwixt the <hi>Popes Holineſſe,</hi> and the <hi>Kings Majeſtie,</hi> the one by his
<hi>conſtitutive</hi> precept <hi>firſt</hi> commanding it under the penalty of a
<hi>Praemunire,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4449:6"/>ſuppoſing it to containe nothing but true <hi>temporall</hi> Allegiance, the other by his <hi>declarative</hi> Breves for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding it, as containing <hi>many things plainely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to faith and ſalvation,</hi> and that both their commandements could not be obeyed, being oppoſits one to the other: And conſidering with my ſelfe <hi>firſt,</hi> that I muſt needs incurre either <hi>ſpirituall</hi> diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, by not obeying the
<hi>Pope,</hi> if his commandement were juſt, or, if otherwiſe, <hi>temporall</hi> diſloyaltie by diſobeying the <hi>King;</hi> and that, according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon doctrine of
<hi>Divines</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">See beneath, num. 26.</note>, the <hi>conſtitutive</hi> precept of a lawfull <hi>Superiour</hi> muſt be obeyed, unleſſe it be clearely
<hi>unjuſt,</hi> according to that which ſhall be ſaid beneath<note n="b" place="margin">num
3c.</note>: <hi>Secondly,</hi> that both the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> may ſometimes erre in their <hi>Iudgements,</hi> and <hi>command</hi> that which is <hi>not juſt,</hi> for that their <hi>judgements are not alwayes grounded upon truth</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Can. <hi>A nobis</hi> de <hi>ſent. Excom.</hi> cap. 28.</note>, <hi>which never deceiveth, nor is deceived, but ſometimes they follow opinion, which may often-times deceive, and be deceived: Thirdly,</hi> that I could not therefore be ſecure in conſcience, by obeying either the <hi>Popes</hi> commandement againſt the <hi>Kings,</hi> or contrariwiſe, with <hi>blinde obedience,</hi> leſt blinded with wilfull ignorance I ſhould <hi>fall into the ditch</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Matth. 15.</note> either of <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> or of <hi>temporall</hi> diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, by not examining with <hi>judgement</hi> of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which of their
<hi>commandements</hi> is just, and therefore to be obeyed, and that my owne <hi>conſcience</hi> must be to mee the inward <hi>judge</hi> of all my actions, and omiſsions.</p>
            <p>And <hi>laſtly,</hi> that I could not ſecure my <hi>conſcience,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4449:7"/>by giving credit only to thoſe, who <hi>write,</hi> and plead in favour of the
<hi>Pope</hi> againſt the <hi>King,</hi> without rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and examining what they who write, and plead for the <hi>King,</hi> doe anſwer in his defence, or contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, conſidering that both of them may relate each others reaſons, and anſwers falſly, lamely, or corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and that in a controverſie, betwixt <hi>two</hi> parties he cannot be accounted an upright
<hi>judge,</hi> who will heare, reade, and examine the reaſons, anſwers, and allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the one ſide, or of the other, only in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as it ſhall pleaſe the <hi>adverſe part</hi> to propound them for his owne advantage, and that therefore to forbid any man, who is to be a <hi>judge</hi> in a controverſie betwixt <hi>two parties</hi> (as in the Court of
<hi>Penance,</hi> every <hi>Ghoſtly Father</hi> is to be a <hi>judge</hi> of whatſoever his
<hi>Penitent</hi> ſhall confeſſe unto him, and in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Court of <hi>Conſcience</hi> every private man is to be his owne <hi>judge</hi>) to reade, heare, and understand the reaſons, and anſwers of either ſide, but only in that manner as his <hi>Adverſary</hi> ſhall propound them, is in very deed no other, than to forbid him to be an <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Iudge.</hi> All which conſidered, to informe my <hi>conſcience</hi> uprightly in this dangerous controverſie of the <hi>Oath,</hi> not betwixt <hi>two inferiour parties,</hi> or betwixt the
<hi>Defendant,</hi> or party ſued, and the <hi>judge,</hi> but betweene <hi>two ſupreme,</hi> and independent <hi>judges</hi> in their degree, the one in <hi>ſpiritualls,</hi> the other in
<hi>temporalls,</hi> contending whether this <hi>new Oath,</hi> which the <hi>one</hi> commandeth, and the <hi>other</hi> forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, be a <hi>temporall,</hi> or a <hi>ſpirituall</hi> thing, containe a profeſsion of true <hi>temporall</hi> Allegiance, or a deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb facs="tcp:4449:7"/>of true <hi>ſpirituall</hi> obedience, I thought it not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure for me, to rely upon the bare relation, and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation either of the one ſide only, or of the other.</p>
            <p>Whereupon to finde out the truth herein according to the capacity of my underſtanding, and to frame my conſcience accordingly, I have diligently read, and examined what bookes ſoever have been publiſhed, as well againſt the <hi>Oath</hi> in favour of the <hi>Pope,</hi> as for it in the <hi>Kings</hi> defence. And I confeſſe ingenuouſly, that thoſe which have beene written in favour of the <hi>Oath,</hi> and of Soveraigne <hi>Princes</hi> not to be depoſed much leſſe to be <hi>murdered,</hi> or <hi>killed</hi> by the <hi>Popes</hi> authority (which is the only principall thing denied therin) have given me ful ſatisfaction in this point, out of which I have at ſundry vacant times, to helpe the weakneſſe of my memory, collected the
<hi>Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and <hi>Obſervations</hi> following, which becauſe they doe clearely convince my underſtanding, and may perchance give the like ſatisfaction to others, and alſo ſtirre up ſome, who are more learned than I am, to defend their <hi>Princes</hi> right, being aſſaulted by ſuch powerfull <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> I thought it neceſſary for divers reaſons to propound them to the publike view of the world, to have them examined by learned
<hi>Divines,</hi> as well in regard of mine owne good, as of the good of others: eſpecially ſeeing that but few of our Engliſh <hi>Prieſts</hi> among ſo many, who in their conſcience approve the <hi>Oath,</hi> dare for ſome world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſpects make knowne their minds herein but only to ſome of their trusty friends, becauſe, as ſome of them who favour the
<hi>Oath,</hi> have ſaid to me in plain
<pb facs="tcp:4449:8"/>termes, the miſery of theſe times is ſuch, that by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, or publikely approving the <hi>Oath,</hi> and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Kings</hi> ſoveraigne right in
<hi>temporalls</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch violent oppoſers thereof, they ſhall gaine little or nothing, in compariſon of that, which they ſhall loſe thereby. So that many <hi>Lay Catholikes</hi> are in daily hazard to loſe their whole eſtates (which is a pitifull thing) for want of being inſtructed by theſe men for worldly ends, in this controverſie of the
<hi>Oath,</hi> which they in their owne conſcience thinke to be very lawfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>One reaſon</hi> therefore, for which I thought it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to publiſh theſe briefe <hi>Explications</hi> of the <hi>Oath,</hi> is the great griefe I have to ſee ſome few of our Engliſh <hi>Prieſts</hi> both <hi>Secular,</hi> and <hi>Religious,</hi> now lately to revive againe this ſcandalous contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie (which for diverſe yeares hath here through ſilence, and connivence been well appeaſed, and to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves most vehemently againſt the <hi>Oath,</hi> though not by publike writings to ſatisfie our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, yet by ſeeking to draw us to embrace their opinions againſt it by violence, and terrours, in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to make a <hi>Schiſme</hi> among us, and to exclude us from the holy
<hi>Sacraments,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> communion, only for <hi>our opinions</hi> (as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves call it) <hi>of the Oath,</hi> againſt the knowne pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of many learned, and vertuous <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt their laſt <hi>Arch-Prieſt,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Doctour <hi>Harriſon,</hi> as diverſe letters of his written to one of his
<hi>Aſſiſtants</hi> (which are yet extant) can give ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient teſtimony. But if theſe men had well obſerved,
<pb facs="tcp:4449:8"/>in what manner Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> writeth againſt the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S.</hi> Aug. <hi>Epht. 48 ad</hi> Vincent. &amp; de Bapt. <hi>contra</hi> Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt.</note> for their breach of <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> unity, and in commendation and excuſe of Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> (who although he oppoſed himſelfe vehemently againſt Pope
<hi>Stephen</hi> in the queſtion of <hi>Baptiſme</hi> admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by <hi>Heretikes,</hi> yet they (till kept <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> communion with each other) doubtleſſe they would have beene fearefull to have proceeded againſt their <hi>Catholike</hi> brethren with ſo little charity, but would have remembred that ſaying of Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S.
<hi>Aug.</hi> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b 3. de <hi>Bapt</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra
<hi>Donat.</hi> 16.</note> that <hi>thoſe men have not charity,</hi> or the <hi>love of God, who love not the unity of the Church,</hi> but feare not to make a breach thereof onely for their
<hi>opinions,</hi> and which for <hi>undoubted</hi> Doctrines <hi>of faith,</hi> they will needs obtrude not onely upon the unlearned, but alſo upon thoſe who are as learned as themſelves.</p>
            <p>An <hi>other reaſon</hi> is, the great pitty I have to ſee ſome <hi>Catholikes</hi> of good account, now lately, by the bad counſell of their <hi>Inſtructours</hi> under a falſe pretence of <hi>Catholike faith</hi> caſt themſelves headlong into manifeſt danger, not onely of a <hi>Praemunire,</hi> to the beggering of themſelves, their wives, and children, but alſo of their <hi>ſoules</hi> (if ignorance doe not excuſe them) by diſobeying the juſt commandement of their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne <hi>Prince</hi> in point of their loyalty, and due obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and giving thereby no ſmall occaſion to <hi>His Majeſtie</hi> to be ſcandalized at our Religion, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it a nouriſher of diſloyaltie, and all us <hi>Roman Catholikes</hi> to be diſloyall Subjects, if the contrarie were not by ſome of us made manifeſt unto him. And is it not a lamentable caſe, and able to move a ſtony
<pb facs="tcp:4449:9"/>heart to teares, that wee <hi>Lay Catholikes,</hi> whom this <hi>Oath</hi> doth chiefly concerne (for <hi>Prieſts</hi> can looſe little, or nothing by refuſing it, being ſubject to greater penalties, then is a <hi>Praemunire,</hi> although by perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding others to refuſe it, becauſe the <hi>Popes</hi> power to <hi>practiſe</hi> the depoſition of <hi>Princes</hi> is denied therein, they may perchance incurre greater danger, as liable to ſuſpicion of diſpoſing the Subjects mindes to Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion when time ſhall ſerve, as any man of judgement may eaſily perceive) that we, I ſay, ſhould by any of our <hi>Engliſh prieſts</hi> (who ſhould rather be a comfort unto us, then add affliction to affliction, knowing the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the lawes, to which we are otherwiſe ſubject in regard of our Religion, if <hi>His Majeſtie</hi> out of his great clemency were not more mercifull unto us) be compelled under paine to be deprived of <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſticall communion,</hi> to looſe all that we have in this world, <hi>liberty, lands,</hi> and <hi>goods</hi> (and which being once loſt by their bad counſell, they can never be able to restore to us backe againe) onely for that we cannot be perſwaded by them to approve as an <hi>undoubted</hi> doctrine of
<hi>faith,</hi> their <hi>opinion</hi> for the <hi>Popes</hi> power to depoſe <hi>Princes</hi> (the onely chiefe thing denied in the <hi>Oath</hi>) which in <hi>France</hi> is not permitted to be publikely taught by any of their <hi>Prieſts</hi> for ſo much as <hi>probable.</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">See the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> of the
<hi>parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>parn</hi> 2 Ian. 1615. printed at <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> by the <hi>Kings</hi> Printers and in the <hi>French Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> tom. 3 the yeare 16.5. pag. 327.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Third reaſon</hi> is, for that <hi>His Majeſtie</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving this controverſie to be kept ſtill on foote more by <hi>faction,</hi> then by <hi>reaſon,</hi> and that the
<hi>Pope</hi> will not bee drawne to name any one <hi>particular</hi> thing, which in the
<hi>Oath</hi> is clearely unlawfull, is reſolved
<pb facs="tcp:4449:9"/>(as I heare) to maintaine his ſupreme <hi>temporall</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority againſt all oppoſers thereof, and that therefore his Subjects ſhould doe well, dutifully to ſhunne this damnable and ſeditious doctrine of depoſing <hi>Princes</hi> by the <hi>Pope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> pretended power which is the maine ſcope, and ſubstance of this <hi>new Oath</hi> (as both the words thereof doe plainely ſhew, and alſo his <hi>Father</hi> of renowned memorie, who was the maker of the law, hath oftentimes declared<note n="f" place="margin">See beneath nu. 3.</note> by publike writings) which opinion is indeed to be abhorred, detested, and abjured by all loyall Subjects in this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> no leſſe then in <hi>France,</hi> where by many <hi>Decrees</hi> of <hi>Parlaments</hi> it is accounted <hi>falſe, damnable, ſeditious,</hi> and bookes written in defence thereof forbidden under paine of <hi>Treaſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See beneath num. 7. and 47</note> and alſo by a ſpeciall <hi>Cenſure</hi> of the <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon Doctours</hi> (to which <hi>ſixteene</hi> French <hi>Ieſuites</hi> promiſed to ſubſcribe) is expreſly <hi>condemned, as new, falſe, erronious, contrary to the word of God</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The <hi>laſt reaſon</hi> is, that great deſire I have not to erre through ignorance (for wilfully by <hi>Gods</hi> grace I will never erre) in the leaſt point which may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the
<hi>Catholike faith,</hi> or my duty to <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Caeſar.</hi> And therefore I would have no man to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that I am ſo audaciouſly arrogant, as to take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me heere to teach learned <hi>Prieſts,</hi> who ought to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct others, their duty, knowing the great weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my owne learning in compariſon of theirs, but rather to bee taught, and inſtructed by them, if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance they ſhall find me to be in an errour, which as ſoone as any of them will vouchſafe to make manifeſt unto me, I promiſe faithfully to retract the ſame forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.
<pb facs="tcp:4449:10"/>For my onely deſire is to informe my conſcience rightly, and to give both to the
<hi>Popes Holineſſe,</hi> and to the <hi>Kings Majeſtie,</hi> that <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> and
<hi>temporall</hi> obedience respectively, which according to the <hi>law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>grounds</hi> of <hi>Catholike Religion</hi> is due to either of them. But if they will be ſilent, and not confute with ſolid reaſons the enſuing <hi>Explications</hi> and
<hi>Obſervations,</hi> and yet will ſtill goe on with their accuſtomed clamours againſt the
<hi>Oath,</hi> and the <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> or approvers thereof, all prudent men may well preſume, that they are not able to convince me of any <hi>errour</hi> and by their ſilence I ſhall be the more confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in my opinion.</p>
            <p>And if their <hi>Anſwere</hi> ſhall bee no other, then by labouring (as ſome of them have lately done) to procure new <hi>Breves,</hi> prohibitions, or Cenſures onely in
<hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> termes (as the former were) after ſo many hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Supplications,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">See <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dringtons</hi> Theologicall D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſputation in the <hi>Epistle,</hi> and the <hi>Concluſion,</hi> his
<hi>Purgation,</hi> and <hi>Sapplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Pope Paul</hi> the Fift. And <hi>Thomas Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,</hi> and <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Greenes</hi> Supplication to Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> the xv.</note> that His <hi>Holineſſe</hi> would bee pleaſed to name ſome one
<hi>particular</hi> thing of <hi>ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> as the former <hi>Breves</hi> have affirmed, to bee in the <hi>Oath,</hi> and conſequently in thoſe <hi>Bookes</hi> which defend it,
<hi>plainly repugnant to faith, and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> they may well ſuppoſe, that thoſe
<hi>Catholikes,</hi> who out of a <hi>pure heart, good conſcience,</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faigned faith,</hi> or obedience both to their <hi>ſpirituall Paſtour,</hi> and alſo to their
<hi>temporall Prince,</hi> deſire to be aſſured of the truth in <hi>particular</hi> (for
<hi>generals</hi> being ſubject to deceit according to that common ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Doloſus verſatur in generalibus,</hi> can give them ſmall ſatisfaction) will not be daunted with ſuch <hi>generall</hi> prohibitions, or Cenſures in a matter of ſo great prejudice, unleſſe they ſhall clearely perceive
<pb facs="tcp:4449:10"/>them to be agreeable to truth, and justice, they being not ignorant, that according to the common Doctrine of <hi>Divines,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Navar
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Enchir.</hi> c. 27. nu. 3. <hi>Cova<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> tom 2. Relect. 1 de <hi>fractis. pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragr.</hi> 7. <hi>Suar.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſp. 4. de
<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r</hi> ſee. 7. and other who
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> prohibitions, and Cenſures, which are unjust, and invalid for want of a just cauſe, and where there is no <hi>Mortall</hi> ſin, doe not bindin conſcience, and will more hurt the ſoules of the procurers then of thoſe, againſt whom they are unjuſtly procured.</p>
            <p>Neither can theſe men bee ignorant, what ſmall account ſome Catholike <hi>Princes,</hi> and their <hi>Subjects</hi> both in former ages,<note n="i" place="margin">See the
<hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>testants</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie trac a. ſee 4.</note> and alſo in theſe our times, have made of ſome <hi>Popes</hi> Breves, Bulls, and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, for that they have ſuppoſed them to bee unjust. And beſides the late <hi>example</hi> of ſome the greatest of our <hi>Secular Prieſts,</hi> in not admitting the <hi>Breves</hi> of this <hi>Popes Holineſſe</hi> being prejudiciall to their pretended ends, may bee a fit <hi>Preſident</hi> to us <hi>Lay Catholikes,</hi> not to admit eaſily, and without due examination ſuch <hi>prohibitions, Breves,</hi> or <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,</hi> which doe tend to the great prejudice of the <hi>Kings</hi> Majeſties <hi>temporall</hi> Soveraigntie, and to the <hi>temporall</hi> ruine of all as his
<hi>Catholike</hi> Subjects.</p>
            <p>Wherefore it were farre more convenient in my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, for the publike peace and unity of the
<hi>Church,</hi> for the honour of the <hi>Sea Apoſtolike,</hi> for the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and particular ſafetie of themſelves, and of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others in their ſoules, bodies, and goods, and for the avoiding of future ſcandals, and contentions; which may ariſe betwixt the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and the <hi>Prieſt-hood</hi> from <hi>new prohibitions,</hi> that theſe men would be a meanes to procure of <hi>His Holineſſe,</hi> that either the former <hi>Breves,</hi> and prohibitions may bee buried with honour in ſilence, and oblivion, and every man
<pb facs="tcp:4449:11"/>left to his owne conſcience, or that ſome <hi>particular</hi> thing in the
<hi>Oath,</hi> which <hi>is plainly repugnant to faith and ſalvation,</hi> be more expreſly declared, that mens minds may not bee troubled, nor the unity of the <hi>Church</hi> diſtracted, onely for <hi>opinions</hi> in things which may concerne the <hi>temporall</hi> rights of
<hi>Princes,</hi> but that, according to the praier of the holy <hi>Church,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">The <hi>Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> in <hi>Easter</hi> weeke.</note> 
               <hi>there may bee one faith of mindes, and piety of actions,</hi> notwithſtanding diverſitie of <hi>opinions,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
<hi>the Church,</hi> which <hi>is the pillar, and ground of truth,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">1
<hi>Tim.</hi> 5. S. <hi>Aug.</hi> l. 1de <hi>Bapt.</hi> contra <hi>Donatiſt. c.</hi> 18.</note> and is no <hi>partie</hi> in this ſtrife, ſhall decide the controverſie, or, as <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> ſpeaketh in the excuſe of <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> untill <hi>by the ſentence of a plenarie Councell the conſent of the whole Church ſhall confirme what is to be followed in this matter.</hi> For ſo long as His <hi>Holineſſe</hi> will permit ſome learned men to write bookes in his behalfe againſt our <hi>King</hi> in things belonging to his ſupreme
<hi>temporall</hi> rights (as doth this <hi>new Oath</hi> of Allegiance) no <hi>prohibitions,</hi> or <hi>Cenſures</hi> can juſtly hinder, but that his <hi>Catholike</hi> Subjects, both
<hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Lay men,</hi> may alſo publiſh in print what may bee anſwered in the <hi>Kings</hi> defence. To conclude, I make no doubt, but that <hi>Truth</hi> will cauſe
<hi>hatred,</hi> as <hi>flatterie doth friends,</hi> but withall I am aſſured, that <hi>Truth is great,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">3. <hi>Eſdr.</hi> 4.</note> and <hi>will prevaile</hi> at laſt, and that <hi>Bleſſed are they who</hi> in the meane time till it prevaile, <hi>doe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffer perſecution,</hi> at whoſe hands ſoever they ſuffer it, for truth, <hi>and juſtice ſake,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>for theirs is the kingdome of heaven.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. 4. l. <hi>penult.</hi> r. <hi>Alſo.</hi> pag. 15. l. 24. r. <hi>Montpillier.</hi> pag. 37 l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> r. <hi>Soocher.</hi> pag. 58. l.
<hi>nit.</hi> in Margent r. <hi>num.</hi> 28.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4449:11"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE OF SIX PRINCIPALL HEADS HANDLED IN THIS TREATISE.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>IRST,</hi> the forme of the <hi>new Oath</hi> is propounded, and every Clauſe thereof briefly explained: And that the maine point denied therein, is onely all true, lawfull, and valid power of the <hi>Pope</hi> to depoſe <hi>Princes,</hi> or to
<hi>practiſe</hi> their depoſition: and that the <hi>Doctrine</hi> which approveth this
<hi>practiſe,</hi> being clearely <hi>falſe,</hi> as approving <hi>open injuſtice,</hi> may be abjured for <hi>falſe,</hi> and conſequently <hi>as impious, damnable,</hi> indirectly, or by a neceſſary conſequence repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4449:12"/>to the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and in this ſenſe <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall,</hi> as both by <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and by the most part of <hi>Catholike</hi> Divines, the word
<hi>[Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call]</hi> is uſually, and properly taken.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> that in <hi>penall</hi> Lawes (as is this for taking the
<hi>Oath</hi>) all <hi>doubtfull</hi> words are to be understood in the more <hi>favourable</hi> ſenſe, and which may make the <hi>Law</hi> to be just and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, and that therefore what <hi>doubtfull</hi> words, or ſentences ſoever are contained in the <hi>Oath,</hi> they must be taken in the more <hi>favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> ſenſe, and which may make the <hi>Oath</hi> to containe no <hi>falſhood,</hi> or <hi>injuſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that <hi>Perjury</hi> is defined by <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines,</hi> to be a <hi>Lye confirmed by Oath,</hi> and that therefore whatſoever may excuſe from
<hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> may alſo excuſe from <hi>Perjury.</hi> And that albeit there bee danger of
<hi>Perjury</hi> to ſweare <hi>doubtfull</hi> words in that ſenſe, which is
<hi>doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> yet to ſweare <hi>doubtfull</hi> words in a true, and determinate ſenſe, and which is not <hi>doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> but cleare, and morally <hi>certaine,</hi> there is no danger of <hi>Perjury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> the difference betwixt <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> and
<hi>Conſtitutive</hi> precepts is declared, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4449:12"/>that becauſe the <hi>Popes Breves</hi> forbidding the <hi>Oath</hi> are
<hi>declarative,</hi> and grounded upon <hi>falſe</hi> reaſons, and ſuppoſitions, therefore
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Catholikes are not bound to obſerve them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> what <hi>Scandall</hi> is, and how many ſorts of
<hi>Scandall</hi> there be, is declared, and that the <hi>refuſing,</hi> not the <hi>taking,</hi> of the <hi>Oath</hi> is truely <hi>ſcandalous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> which is the <hi>ſafer way</hi> is declared, and that it is <hi>ſafer</hi> to take the <hi>Oath,</hi> than to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe it; yea, and that to refuſe it, is <hi>not ſafe</hi> at all: and the <hi>example</hi> of chooſing the <hi>more ſafe,</hi> and the <hi>more probable Phyſicke</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed, and ſhewed, that it is no fit
<hi>example</hi> to diſſwade any man from taking the <hi>Oath,</hi> being commanded by the
<hi>conſtitutive</hi> precept of our <hi>Soveraigne Prince.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="oath_of_allegiance">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:4449:13"/>
            <head>THE FORME OF THE new Oath of Allegiance divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into eight parts or Clauſes, as they are explained in this TREATISE.</head>
            <q>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>I. A. B.</hi> Doc truly, and ſincerely acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, profeſſe, teſtifie, and declare in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience before God, and the World; That our Soveraigne Lord King CHARLES is lawfull, and rightfull King of this Realme, and of all other His <hi>Majesties</hi> Dominions and Countries.</p>
               <p n="2">2 And that the <hi>Pope</hi> neither of himſelfe, nor by any authority of the Church, or ſee of <hi>Rome,</hi> or by any other meanes with any other, hath any power, or authoritie to depoſe <hi>the King,</hi> or to diſpoſe any of His <hi>Majesties</hi> Kingdomes, or Dominions, or to authorize any forren Prince to invade, or annoy Him, or His Countries, or to diſcharge any of His Subjects of their Alleagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, or Obedience to His <hi>Majestie,</hi> or to give licence, or leave to any of them to beare Armes, raiſe Tumults, or to offer any violence, or hurt to His <hi>Majesties</hi> Royall Perſon, State, or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or to any of His
<hi>Majesties</hi> Subjects within His <hi>Majesties</hi> Dominions.</p>
               <p n="3">3 And I doe ſweare from my heart, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any Declaration, or ſentence of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4449:13"/>Excommunication, or Deprivation, made or granted, or to be made or granted by the <hi>Pope,</hi> or His Succeſſours, or by any Authoritie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived, or to be derived from Him, or His See againſt the ſaid <hi>King,</hi> His Heires, or Succeſſors, or any Abſolution of the ſaid Subjects from their Obedience; I will beare faith, and true Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagiance to His <hi>Majestie,</hi> His Heires, and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours, and Him, and Them will defend to the uttermoſt of my power againſt all Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and Attempts whatſoever, which ſhall be made againſt His, or their Perſons, their Crown or Dignitie, by reaſon, or colour of any ſuch Sentence, or Declaration, or otherwiſe; and will doe my beſt endevour to diſcloſe, and make knowne unto His <hi>Majestie,</hi> His Heires and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours, all Treaſons, and Trayterous Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies, which I ſhall know or heare of to be againſt Him, or any of them.</p>
               <p n="4">4 And I doe further ſweare, that I doe from my heart abhorre, deteſt, and abjure as impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and hereticall, this damnable doctrine, and poſition, <hi>That</hi> Princes, <hi>which be excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, or deprived by the</hi> Pope, <hi>may be depoſed, or murthered by their Subjects, or any other what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 And I doe beleeve, and in conſcience am reſolved, that neither the <hi>Pope,</hi> nor any Perſon whatſoever, hath power to abſolve me of this Oath, or any part thereof.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Which I acknowledge by good, and full authoritie to be lawfully miniſtred unto me, and

<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4449:14"/>doe renounce all Pardons, and diſpenſations to the contrarie.</p>
               <p n="7">7 And all theſe things I doe plainely, and ſincerely acknowledge, and ſweare, according to the expreſſe words by mee ſpoken, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the plaine, and common ſenſe, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the ſame words, without any equivocation, or mentall evaſion, or ſecret re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation whatſoever.</p>
               <p n="8">8 And I doe make this Recognition and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement, heartily, willingly, and truely upon the true faith of a Chriſtian. <hi>So helpe me God.</hi>
               </p> 
            </q>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="clause">
            <head>The first Clauſe explained.</head>
            <p n="1">1 THe <hi>First</hi> Clauſe, <hi>I A B,</hi> &amp;c. all <hi>Engliſh</hi> Catholikes (although otherwiſe vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment impugners of the <hi>Oath,</hi> as Doctor <hi>Kelliſon</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">In his <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe</hi> of the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> and the <hi>Prince,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. <hi>nu.</hi> 12.</note>, and Father <hi>Parſons</hi>) doe willingly admit; for that every <hi>Engliſh Catholike</hi> (ſaith Father <hi>Parſons</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>In his Booke entitled,</hi> The Iudgement of a Catholike Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh man,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> part. <hi>1.</hi> nu. <hi>22.</hi> pag. <hi>13.16.</hi>
               </note>) will ſweare and acknowledge moſt willingly all thoſe parts, and Clauſes of the <hi>Oath,</hi> which doe any way appertaine to the Civill and Temporall obedience due to His <hi>Majestie,</hi> whom he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth for his true and lawfull King, and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne over all His Dominions. Neither can there be any difficultie therein, except onely to know, what is that, which in this Clauſe, and the next, by <hi>vertue</hi> of the <hi>expreſſe words,</hi> and the <hi>plaine,</hi> and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4449:14"/>
               <hi>common ſenſe</hi> of them (to which the <hi>Seventh</hi> Clauſe expreſly bindeth the Swearer) I am bound to <hi>ſweare</hi> immediately; to wit, whether by
<hi>force</hi> of the <hi>words</hi> I muſt <hi>ſweare</hi> immediately, <hi>That our Soveraigne Lord,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And that the Pope,</hi> &amp;c. or only my ſincere
<hi>acknowledgement</hi> thereof. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in regard of the <hi>matter,</hi> it is lawfull to
<hi>ſweare</hi> them both, that is, both the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and alſo my ſincere
<hi>acknowledgement</hi> of them, and therefore we need not to contend about the words: Yet it is very probable, if not certain, that by <hi>force</hi> of the <hi>words</hi> I am bound to
<hi>ſweare</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately only my ſincere <hi>acknowledgement.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all the
<hi>ſwearing</hi> both in this Clauſe, and the next, conſiſteth only in thoſe words
<hi>[Before God]</hi> which being taken away, there would be no <hi>ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> or
<hi>Oath</hi> at all, in affirming, or denying any thing contained in theſe <hi>two</hi> Clauſes. And the plaine meaning of theſe words <hi>[Before God, and the World]</hi> is this, that I A B doe call God, and the World to witneſſe, that <hi>I doe truly,</hi> that is, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faignedly, <hi>and ſincerely acknowledge, profeſſe, teſtifie and declare in my conſcience, That our Soveraigne Lord,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And that the Pope,</hi> &amp;c. although, as I ſaid, in <hi>regard</hi> of the <hi>matter,</hi> it is lawfull to <hi>ſweare</hi> them both.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="clause">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:4449:15"/>
            <head>The ſecond Clauſe explained.</head>
            <p n="2">2 IN the <hi>Second</hi> Clauſe, <hi>And that the Pope,</hi> &amp;c. (which is the root and ground of all the Branches following) there is no ſuch difficultie as ſome pretend, if wee duely conſider the expreſſe words thereof, and the occaſion, end, and reaſon, for which this <hi>new Oath</hi> was deviſed. For, as <hi>Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez</hi> doth well obſerve,<note place="margin">Suarez lib <hi>6.</hi> de Leg. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vpon the will, and intention of the</hi> Law-maker <hi>(which is the ſoule of the Law) the ſubſtance, and force of the Law doth chiefly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend. Whereupon, if by any meanes the will of the</hi> Law-maker <hi>may be knowne, according to it eſpecially we muſt interpret the words of the</hi> Law,
<hi>becauſe that is the true interpretation of the</hi> Law, <hi>by which we fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the will, and meaning of the</hi> Law-maker: <hi>not his will meerely</hi> internall, <hi>but as it is expreſſed by words, becauſe a</hi> Law <hi>is not enacted by the</hi> Princes <hi>will, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe by the</hi> words <hi>of the</hi> Law <hi>it be ſufficiently expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſeeing that the</hi> will <hi>alone is not of it ſelfe ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to binde, neither alſo is it ſufficient, that it bee privately knowne by ſome other way, but it is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that it be ſufficiently contained in the</hi> Law <hi>it ſelfe. And eſpecially we muſt conſider the beginning,</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, <hi>or</hi> Preamble <hi>of the</hi> Law, <hi>and joyne with it the rest which follow: for to the</hi> beginning <hi>if there be no other let, all that followeth is to be applyed, becauſe in the</hi> beginning, <hi>or</hi> Preamble <hi>of the Conſtitution is uſually contained the</hi> finall end, <hi>cauſe, and reaſon,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4449:15"/>which chiefly moveth the</hi> Law-maker, <hi>and which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rray is a ſure meanes to finde out his will, and meaning, and by which the ambiguitie of any doubtfull word, or ſentence is chiefly to be determined.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Now upon the occaſion, and diſcovery of thoſe barbarous <hi>Powder-Traytours,</hi> who were all of them <hi>Roman Catholikes,</hi> and, as it appeareth by their confeſſions, grounded their divelliſh Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie chiefly upon the <hi>Popes</hi> power to deprive
<hi>Princes</hi> of their <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> and <hi>Lives</hi> for the good of Religion: The
<hi>Kings</hi> Majeſtie knowing right well, that many other <hi>Roman Catholikes</hi> did from their hearts deteſt, and abhorre ſuch Trayterous and Diabolicall <hi>practiſes,</hi> and the wicked <hi>grounds</hi> thereof, thought it needfull for the better diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering and repreſſing of ſuch bloudie Aſſaſinates, and their diſciples, to deviſe, and eſtabliſh in the next <hi>Parliament</hi> following ſuch an <hi>Oath,</hi> wherein true
<hi>temporall</hi> Allegiance due to all <hi>temporal Princes</hi> what Religion ſoever they profeſſe, ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, and no true <hi>ſpirituall</hi> obedience due to the
<hi>Popes</hi> Holineſſe ſhould be denied, and yet the wicked <hi>principles</hi> of that moſt damnable <hi>Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie</hi> ſhould be detected, and abjured. Whereupon the
<hi>Parliament,</hi> in the very beginning, or <hi>Preamble</hi> of the <hi>Oath</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 3. <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cobi cap.</hi> 4. <hi>ſect.</hi> And for the better triall, &amp;c.</note>, ſetteth down the <hi>end,</hi> and <hi>reaſon</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to wit, <hi>for the better triall how His</hi> Majeſties <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſtand affected in point of their loyaltie, and due obedience, which</hi> (as afterwards in the next<note n="d" place="margin">Anno
<hi>7.</hi> Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobi cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Seſsion</hi> they declare) <hi>every true and well affected Subject not onely by the bond of Alleagiance, but alſo by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of Almightie</hi> GOD <hi>ought to beare to His</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:4449:16"/>Majeſtie, <hi>his Heires, and Succeſſours.</hi> And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, the
<hi>Kings Majeſtie</hi> Himſelfe hath often by publike writings<note n="e" place="margin">In his
<hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition</hi> pag. 9. and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <hi>Apologie</hi> for the <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th,</hi> pag.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; 9.</note> in expreſſe words declared, that in <hi>this Oath</hi> He intended to demand of His Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects nothing elſe, than
<hi>a profeſsion of that temporall Alleagiance, and Civill obdience, which all ſubjects by the Law of</hi> GOD <hi>and Nature, doe owe to their lawfull</hi> Prince, <hi>with a promiſe to reſist, and diſcloſe all contrary uncivill violence,</hi> and <hi>to make a true di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, not betwixt</hi> Catholikes <hi>and</hi> Proteſtants, <hi>but betwixt</hi> Catholikes <hi>of quiet diſpoſition, and in all other things good Subjects, and ſuch other</hi> Catholikes <hi>as in their hearts maintained the like violent bloudie Maximes, as the Powder-traytours did.</hi> Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on He <hi>cauſed the lower Houſe of</hi> Parliament, <hi>who at the firſt would have had the</hi> Oath <hi>to containe a deniall of the</hi> Popes <hi>power to</hi> excommunicate <hi>Him, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that Clauſe: So carefull was He,</hi> that nothing
<hi>ſhould be contained in this</hi> Oath, <hi>except the profeſsion of naturall Alleagiance, and civill, and temporall Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</hi> He ſaid [<hi>in this</hi> Oath] <hi>for as the</hi> Oath <hi>of Supremacie,</hi> ſaith His Majeſtie, <hi>was deviſed for put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a difference betweene</hi> Papiſts, <hi>and them of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion; ſo was</hi> this Oath <hi>ordained for making a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene the civilly obedient</hi> Papiſts, <hi>and the perverſe diſciples of the Powder treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>First,</hi> therefore, in this Clauſe is not denied the power, authoritie, right, or title, which tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall <hi>Princes,</hi> or <hi>Common-wealths</hi> have, or may pretend to have in <hi>temporals,</hi> as to make warre, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade, annoy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon juſt cauſe. For this <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> power either of <hi>Princes,</hi> or <hi>Common-wealths,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:4449:16"/>and conſequently of the <hi>Pope,</hi> as he is a <hi>temporall Prince,</hi> is not in this Clauſe medled withall, neither is there any thing concerning it affirmed, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied therein, as the expreſſe words doe plainely ſhew, but only concerning the
<hi>power,</hi> and <hi>authority,</hi> which the <hi>Pope</hi> formally as he is <hi>Pope, Biſhop of Rome,</hi> or ſupreme <hi>ſpirituall Pastour,</hi> or <hi>Prince,</hi> either of himſelfe, or by any other meanes with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hath to depoſe the <hi>King,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Secondly,</hi> neither in this Clauſe is denied that that power, or authoritie, which the <hi>Pope,</hi> as <hi>Pope,</hi> hath to <hi>command</hi> temporall things, as
<hi>invadings, annoyings,</hi> &amp;c. in order to <hi>ſpirituall</hi> good, or, which is all one, to concurre therein with others, who have, or may pretend to have ſuch power to <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade, annoy,</hi> &amp;c. by way only of <hi>morall</hi> influence, or motion, as by <hi>hiring, perſwading,</hi> or <hi>comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding;</hi> neither can the words of this Clauſe, being taken properly, admit this ſenſe. For to have power or authoritie to doe a thing, as to <hi>invade, annoy,</hi> &amp;c. is a farre different thing, than to have power, or authority only to
<hi>command</hi> the doing thereof, or to concurre by way only of <hi>morall</hi> influence, with others who have true, and lawful power to doe it. As to have <hi>art,</hi> or skill to
<hi>paint,</hi> is a farre different thing, than to hire or <hi>command</hi> a <hi>Painter</hi> who hath skil, to <hi>paint,</hi> or to concur with him to the making of a <hi>picture</hi> by way only of <hi>moral</hi> influence, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Neither can a <hi>King,</hi> who hireth, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth a
<hi>Painter</hi> to make ſuch a <hi>picture,</hi> bee truly ſaid to make or paint that
<hi>picture,</hi> or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre to the painting thereof, as having himſelfe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4449:17"/>
               <hi>art,</hi> or skill to paint it. And in like manner it is to be ſaid that a <hi>Pope,</hi> who by way onely of <hi>morall</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, as by perſwading, hiring, or comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, concurreth to the invading of a <hi>King</hi> with others, who have perchance true and lawfull power to invade him, be truely ſaid to invade that <hi>King,</hi> as having himſelfe true and lawfull power to invade Him, of which power and authoritie to <hi>invade, annoy,</hi> &amp;c. and not of <hi>morall</hi> influence, or of power onely to <hi>command</hi> Invaſions,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> this Clauſe expreſly ſpeaketh. And therefore albeit we ſhould falſly ſuppoſe (which ſome doe greatly, but perniciouſly, indiſcreetly, and to no purpoſe urge againſt this Clauſe) that the Civill <hi>Common-wealth</hi> in ſome caſe hath power to puniſh and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe her Soveraigne <hi>Prince,</hi> and that the <hi>Pope</hi> may concurre with her therein by way of <hi>morall</hi> influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or motion (which nevertheleſſe for
<hi>practiſe,</hi> which is chiefly to be regarded, is <hi>certainly</hi> falſe, for the ſame reaſon, for which as I wil ſhew forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, it is <hi>certainly</hi> falſe, that the
<hi>Pope</hi> hath not any true, and lawfull power to <hi>depoſe,</hi> or practiſe the depoſition of <hi>Princes,</hi> becauſe ſo long as it is but <hi>probable</hi> inſpeculation, or, which is all one, ſo long as it is but an opinion, or controverſie among
<hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers,</hi> and <hi>Divines,</hi> the <hi>Prince</hi> being in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, cannot upon any <hi>probable,</hi> or controverſed power or title, be deprived thereof without
<hi>open injuſtice</hi>) yet this being falſly ſuppoſed, would no way impugne this Branch of the <hi>Oath,</hi> which ſpeaketh not of the <hi>Popes</hi> concurring with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to
<hi>depoſing, invading, annoying,</hi> &amp;c. by way
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4449:17"/>onely of <hi>morall</hi> influence, but onely of his <hi>Power, or authority to depoſe, invade, annoy</hi> &amp;c. or of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring with any other to the doing of thoſe acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as having himſelfe <hi>true power,</hi> and <hi>authority</hi> to doe them.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Neither <hi>thirdly</hi> can any man with any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, charity, or reverent reſpect to the <hi>Kings</hi> Majeſtie conceive, that He would by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament</hi> have all His Subjects to <hi>ſweare,</hi> or ſincerely to acknowledge by Oath that to be true, which <hi>Himſelfe,</hi> and all the Chriſtian world know to be clearely falſe, to wit, that the <hi>Pope,</hi> as <hi>Pope,</hi> hath not any power to depoſe the <hi>King,</hi> as alſo other <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> ſo much as in the opinion of the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelfe, and of many other <hi>Divines,</hi> who are of his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For His <hi>Majestie</hi> knew right well, and which being a thing ſo manifeſt, no man of any judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can deny, which therefore Father
<hi>Leſsins,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Leſſins</hi> in his <hi>Singleton de Diſcuſsione de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creti</hi> Lateran. concilii <hi>part</hi> 2. num. 38.</note> and Docter
<hi>Kelliſon,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">In his <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe</hi> of the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> and the <hi>Prince</hi> &amp;c. cap. 11. num. 7. pag. 241.</note> doe in expreſſe words ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that <hi>a power, which is not altogether cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi> but onely
<hi>probable,</hi> or in controverſie, <hi>cannot be a</hi> ſufficient <hi>ground, whereby immediately any man may be puniſhed, and deprived of any his right, and Dominion,</hi> nor can be
<hi>practiſed</hi> without <hi>open in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice.</hi> And conſequently that a <hi>power to depoſe,</hi> which is onely <hi>probable,</hi> is not <hi>any true,</hi> reall, law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſufficient, and valid <hi>power to depoſe,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for <hi>practiſe</hi> neither in law, nor conſcience to be accounted <hi>any power</hi> at all: ſeeing that <hi>power,</hi> and <hi>practiſe</hi> are <hi>correlatives,</hi> which <hi>doe mutually in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre, and deſtroy each other,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Ariſt. <hi>in Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicam.</hi> cap. 3.</note> and where there can be no <hi>true,</hi> reall, and lawfull <hi>effect,</hi> or <hi>practiſe,</hi> there
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4449:18"/>is no <hi>true,</hi> reall, and lawfull <hi>power.</hi> For <hi>in vaine is that power,</hi> and therefore <hi>none,</hi> ſeeing that <hi>God, and Nature doe nothing in vaine,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt.</hi> lib. <hi>3.</hi> de Coelo
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea. <hi>32</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to effect,</hi> or <hi>practiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 And that it is a Doctrine truely <hi>probable, it</hi> being approved by ſo many learned <hi>Divines,</hi> who have ſeen and examined all the arguments on either ſide, nor grounded upon any reaſon, or principle which is cleerely falſe, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath not pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to <hi>depoſe Princes,</hi> it is manifeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt</hi> by the <hi>Acts,</hi> and proceedings of the <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon Doctours</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">See the <hi>French Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie</hi> tom. 2. <hi>ad</hi> Ann. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. <hi>p.</hi> 597. <hi>&amp; ſeq.</hi>
               </note> againſt the <hi>Engliſh controverſie</hi> of <hi>Becanus,</hi> who held, that it <hi>is certaine,</hi> and <hi>out of all controverſie among Catholikes,</hi> that the <hi>Pope hath power to deprive Princes of their Kingdomes, yea and of their lives,</hi> falſly pretending the
<hi>High Prieſt</hi> in the <hi>old Law</hi> to have the ſame authority, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the
<hi>Pope</hi> in the new.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> by the Cenſure of the ſaid <hi>Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Facultie</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">This <hi>Cenſure</hi> is printed at <hi>Paris</hi> in <hi>Latin,</hi> and may bee ſeen in <hi>French</hi> in the <hi>French Merc</hi> tom 11. <hi>ad</hi> Ann. 1626. <hi>p.</hi>
9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and ſee it beneath nu. 44.</note> againſt the Doctrine of <hi>Santarellus,</hi> which teacheth, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>Princes</hi> for hereſie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> by the publike <hi>Declaration</hi> of <hi>Sixteene</hi> the chiefeſt
<hi>Ieſuites</hi> of France dated the ſixteenth of <hi>March</hi> 1626; and exhibited to the
<hi>French King,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">See the <hi>French Mere.</hi> tom. 11 <hi>ad</hi> An.
1626. <hi>pag.</hi> 92.</note> wherein <hi>they renounce, and deteſt the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of</hi> Santarellus <hi>as wicked,</hi> in <hi>that which concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Perſons of</hi> Kings,
<hi>their Authority, and their States</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Promiſing to ſubſcribe to the cenſure, which ſhall be made againſt that pernicious Doctrine by the Clergie, or the Sorbon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> by the publike Declaration of <hi>three</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:4449:18"/>French <hi>Biſhops,</hi> to wit, of <hi>Auranches,</hi> of <hi>Charters,</hi> and of <hi>Soiſsons,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">See the <hi>Fren. Merc.</hi> tom. 11.
<hi>ad</hi> Ann. 1626, <hi>pag.</hi> 105.</note> wherein alſo they inſinuate, that the
<hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>France</hi> in their Generall Aſſemblie did agree with them in theſe <hi>three</hi> propoſitions: 1. <hi>That it is not lawfull to rebell, or take Armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the</hi> King <hi>for any cauſe, or occaſion whatſoever.</hi> 2. <hi>That all Subjects are bound to obey the</hi> Kings, <hi>and that no perſon can diſpence with their Oath of Allegiance.</hi> 3. <hi>That the</hi> King <hi>cannot be depoſed by any power what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, nor under any pretext, or occaſion whatſoever,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> by the <hi>firſt Article,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">See the <hi>Fren. Merc.</hi> tom. 3. <hi>ad.</hi> Ann. 1615. <hi>pag.</hi> 235.</note> or Oath of <hi>France</hi> (which in ſubſtance is all one with our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Oath) agreed upon in the yeare 1615 by the <hi>Third Estates,</hi> or Lower Houſe of <hi>Parlament,</hi> wherein of <hi>two hundred</hi> Perſons, or thereabout, there were but <hi>ſix Proteſtants,</hi> and no one
<hi>Proteſtant</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the making thereof, or privie thereunto, as <hi>Preſident Miron,</hi> Speaker for the Houſe, did pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely before them all, <hi>Cardinall Peron</hi> being then preſent, confidently affirme<note n="p" place="margin">Ibid. <hi>p.</hi> 312.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> by the uniforme conſent of all the <hi>French Prelates</hi> in the generall Aſſembly of all the Eſtates held the yeare 1614. 1615. <hi>who</hi> (as the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Montxillier</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Ibid <hi>p.</hi> 253.</note> and the Lord
<hi>Cardinall Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Ibid. <hi>p.</hi> 270.</note> ſent by the
<hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> Chamber to the <hi>Third Eſtates</hi> about their <hi>Firſt Article</hi> doe affirme) <hi>were willing</hi> to joyne with the <hi>Third Eſtates</hi> in this common Article, That it is not <hi>lawfull for any man to touch the perſon of their Kings for any crime, or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any cauſe or occaſion what ſoever; which they offered to ſigne not onely with their hearts, but alſo with their blouds, and to cry Anathema, eternall malediction, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4449:19"/>damnation againſt all thoſe, who ſhall attempt to kill their</hi> Kings
<hi>for any crime, or upon any cauſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</hi> And nevertheleſſe (as
<hi>Preſident Miron</hi> very well anſwered the ſaid <hi>Cardinalls</hi> Oration <hi>ex tempore</hi>) the <hi>Doctrine of depoſing, and of killing</hi> Kings, <hi>are Couſin Germans,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Ibid. <hi>p.</hi> 320.</note> for that they proceed from the ſame roote, and <hi>offspring</hi> of the <hi>Popes</hi> power to diſpoſe of all temporalls, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently not onely of <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> but alſo of <hi>Lives</hi> in order to
<hi>ſpirituall</hi> good; and alſo (as the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Conday</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Ibid. <hi>p</hi> 332.</note> in his learned, and Religious ſpeech to the
<hi>King</hi> ſitting in <hi>Councell</hi> doth well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve) <hi>the Doctrine of depoſing Princes, as a thread in a needle,</hi> leadeth to uſurpations, <hi>Rebellions, and the murthering of Soveraigne Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> and laſtly by the teſtimonie of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall Peron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Card. Peron <hi>in his great</hi> Fren. Reply. <hi>cap.</hi> 91 <hi>pag.</hi>
633.</note> who expreſly ſaith, that <hi>this controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> concerning the
<hi>Popes</hi> power indirectly in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralls, <hi>ought not to hinder the reunion of thoſe, who ſhould deſire to be reconciled to the Church:</hi> To omit the <hi>Decrees</hi> of the Parlament of <hi>Paris</hi> forbidding under paine of <hi>Treaſon</hi> the <hi>Treatiſe</hi> of
<hi>Cardinall Bellarmine</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">See the <hi>Fren. Merc.</hi> tom. 2.
<hi>ad</hi> An. 1610. <hi>p.</hi> 19.</note> againſt Doctour <hi>Barclay,</hi> the <hi>Defenſio Fidei Catholicae,</hi> &amp;c. Of <hi>Suarez:</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Idem tom. 3. <hi>ad</hi> An. 1614. <hi>pag.</hi> 441. See alſo tom. 3. <hi>ad</hi> An. 1615. <hi>pag.</hi> 327.</note> the
<hi>Treatiſe</hi> of <hi>Santarellus de Haereſi</hi> &amp;c.<note n="y" place="margin">Idem. tom
11 <hi>ad</hi> An 1626. <hi>pag.</hi> 87.</note> The burning of Doctour <hi>Schulckenius</hi> Apologie for <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Widdrington</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Idem. tom. 3. <hi>ad</hi> An. 1623. <hi>pag.</hi> 277.</note> by the ſentence of the
<hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voſt</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> beſides many learned <hi>Catholikes</hi> both of our owne Nation, as Biſhop <hi>Watſon,</hi> Abot <hi>Fecknam,</hi> Doctour <hi>Cole,</hi> Iohn
<hi>Harpſfield,</hi> Nicolas <hi>Harpſfield,</hi> Iohn <hi>Hart,</hi> Iames
<hi>Boſgrave,</hi> the <hi>Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4449:19"/>Priests</hi> proteſtation, and alſo of other, related, and confirmed by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">In his conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Mr Fizherbert p. 1. <hi>per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Widdrington</hi> againſt all the exceptions, which Doctour <hi>Schulckenius</hi> hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt them: All which doe ſo clearely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the <hi>probabilitie</hi> of this Doctrine, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth the <hi>Popes</hi> power to depoſe <hi>Princes,</hi> that no man of any reading can from his heart now deny the ſame.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Wherefore the plaine meaning of this clauſe is, <hi>[That the Pope]</hi> that is, properly, and formally as Pope <hi>[neither of himſlefe]</hi> that is, as a ſole, and totall Efficient cauſe <hi>[nor by the authority of the Church, or See of Rome]</hi> that is, as an inſtrument or Miniſter of the Church, or See of Rome <hi>[or by any other meanes]</hi> that is, as a Principall Agent, uſing ſome helps or meanes, as his inſtruments <hi>[with any other]</hi> that is, as a Partiall Agent concurring par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially with ſome other. Which
<hi>Partiall Agents</hi> although they have not alwaies <hi>compleat</hi> and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient power to produce the effect ſeverally, and by one of themſelves alone, yet if they be properly
<hi>Partiall Agents,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">See the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers upon 2. <hi>Phyſ.</hi> or 5. <hi>Metaph.</hi> where they treate of the Efficient Cauſe, and alſo ſhew the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt a Phyſicall or Reall Agent, and a Morall, who ſometimes is reputed a Princi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent <hi>in gene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> moris,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th nothing.</note> they muſt alwaies have in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the ſame <hi>ſpecificall</hi> active or virtuall power, by which they concurre joyntly with each other to the producing thereof: As <hi>two men</hi> drawing a
<hi>Ship,</hi> which one of them alone is not able to draw. And therefore a <hi>Maister,</hi> who onely by <hi>morall</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, as by <hi>commanding,</hi> or hyring, concurreth with his
<hi>Servants</hi> to the drawing of the <hi>Ship,</hi> is not properly a <hi>Partiall Agent</hi> concurring with them, nor is ſaid to draw <hi>partially</hi> with them the <hi>Ship,</hi> but hee is a <hi>Principall Agent</hi> of a farre different
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4449:20"/>kinde, and nature, to wit, <hi>Morall;</hi> and his <hi>Servants,</hi> as drawing by his appointment, are onely his <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Instruments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>[Hath any power or authority]</hi> that is, not meerely <hi>probable,</hi> or in the conceit, opinion, or ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation of the <hi>Pope,</hi> and of many other learned men, for this, as I ſaid, is for <hi>practiſe</hi> to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no power at all, but true, reall, lawfull, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and valid <hi>power, or authority [to depoſe the King]</hi> that is, by his definitive ſentence to deprive him of his <hi>Regall</hi> authority, and to make him to true, and rightfull <hi>King,</hi> but a private man: <hi>[or to dispoſe any of his [Kingdomes, or Dominions]</hi> that is, to take them away from him, and to give them to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which ſuppoſeth, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath power to <hi>depoſe</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and to deprive Him of his <hi>Royall</hi> right and Dominion: <hi>[or to diſcharge any of his Subjects of their obedience]</hi> becauſe, according to Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and
<hi>Suarez,</hi> every <hi>Subject</hi> by the law of <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bell.</hi> in Tract. contra <hi>Barcla.</hi> cap. 21. p 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2 <hi>Suar.</hi> in Defen. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> lib 6. cap. 3. num.
6.</note> and <hi>Nature,</hi> oweth true <hi>obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> and Allegiance to his lawfull
<hi>Prince,</hi> ſo long as He remaineth Prince: <hi>[or to authorize]</hi> that is, to give authority <hi>to any forraigne Princes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade, or annoy Him, or His Countries:</hi> Becauſe all the <hi>authority,</hi> which temporall <hi>Princes</hi> have in temporalls, to <hi>invade, or annoy</hi> &amp;c. they have not derived from the <hi>authority,</hi> or <hi>commandement</hi> of the <hi>Pope,</hi> as he is <hi>Pope,</hi> but granted them by the Law of <hi>God, Nature,</hi> or
<hi>Nations:</hi> [<hi>or to give licence, or leave to any of His Subjects to beare Armes</hi> &amp;c.] Becauſe the <hi>Pope,</hi> as <hi>Pope,</hi> hath no ſuch <hi>authority, licence,</hi> or <hi>leave himſelf,</hi> and therfore cannot give it to others.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4449:20"/>And by this is eaſily anſwered the common <hi>objection</hi> urged againſt this Clauſe, that no man can <hi>ſweare</hi> a probable opinion to be certainly falſe, but it is a <hi>probable</hi> opinion at the leaſt, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath power to depoſe <hi>Princes,</hi> or, which in ſubſtance is all one, no man can ſweare, that the
<hi>Pope</hi> hath not <hi>any power</hi> to depoſe the <hi>King,</hi> ſeeing that he hath a
<hi>probable power</hi> to depoſe him; but a <hi>probable power</hi> to depoſe is <hi>ſome power.</hi> For it is not a <hi>probable</hi> opinion in <hi>practiſe,</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it be in
<hi>meere ſpeculation,</hi> and abſtracting from <hi>practiſe,</hi> that the Pope hath power to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe</hi> Princes, or to <hi>practiſe</hi> their <hi>depoſition,</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, which is moſt manifeſt, that it is not <hi>alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether certaine,</hi> but onely
<hi>probable,</hi> and in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie among learned Catholikes that he hath power to depoſe them, unleſſe we will abſurdly admit, that it is a <hi>probable opinion,</hi> that the Pope may lawfully commit open <hi>injustice.</hi> Neither is a meere <hi>probable</hi> power any true, lawfull, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient power to depoſe, puniſh, or diſpoſſeſſe (of which power onely this Clauſe is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood) and therefore for <hi>practiſe</hi> neither in law, nor conſcience to be accounted <hi>any power</hi> at all.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="clause">
            <head>The Third Clauſe explained.</head>
            <p n="10">10 THe <hi>Third</hi> Clauſe, <hi>Alſo I doe ſweare</hi> &amp;c. hath in it no difficulty, ſuppoſing the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4449:21"/>former, to which it hath relation, as <hi>practiſe</hi> hath to
<hi>power.</hi> For if it be lawfull to <hi>acknowledge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God,</hi> that the <hi>Pope hath not by any meanes,</hi> either of <hi>Excommunication, Deprivation, Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or any other <hi>Sentence,</hi> or <hi>Declaration,</hi> any true, lawfull, ſufficient, and valid power, or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to <hi>depoſe</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and to make him no <hi>King,</hi> and conſequently to diſcharge or <hi>abſolve</hi> his Subjects from their Allegiance, it cleerely followeth, that I may alſo <hi>promiſe</hi> by Oath, that <hi>notwithstanding any ſentence of Excommunication, Deprivation, Abſolution, or other Declaration made, or to be made by the</hi> Pope, <hi>or his Succeſſours, againſt the</hi> King, <hi>his Heires, or Succeſſours,</hi> Firſt, <hi>I will beare faith, and true Allegiance to His</hi> Majeſty, <hi>his Heires, and Succeſſors:</hi> Secondly, <hi>I will defend Him, and them to the uttermoſt of my power againſt all conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies</hi> &amp;c. And thirdly, <hi>I will doe my beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to diſcloſe, and make knowne unto His Majeſtie, his Heires and Succeſſours, all Treaſons, and Traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Conſpiracies</hi> &amp;c. Becauſe to performe theſe <hi>three things</hi> every faithfull Subiect, although he neither had, nor ſhould make any expreſſe <hi>Oath,</hi> or promiſe to performe them, is bound by the abſolute law of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> to performe, ſo long as the <hi>King</hi> remaineth <hi>King,</hi> and cannot bee deprived of his
<hi>Regall</hi> authority by the <hi>Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>Secondly,</hi> in this Clauſe is not meddled withall, but rather ſuppoſed, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n denied the <hi>Popes</hi> power to
<hi>Excommunicate,</hi> as King <hi>Iames</hi> of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4449:21"/>renowned memorie hath by<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> praefat. Monitor.
<hi>pag 11.12</hi> &amp; in Conſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daciorum Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, mendacio <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> publike writings not onely declared to all Chriſtian <hi>Princes,</hi> but alſo very well proved againſt <hi>Card. Bellarmine.</hi> But this onely is here denied, that <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> being a <hi>ſpirituall</hi> Cenſure can worke this <hi>temporall</hi> effect, as to make a <hi>King,</hi> no <hi>King,</hi> but only of a Chriſtian, as a <hi>Heathen,</hi> and a <hi>Publican,</hi> and to deprive him of
<hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> communion, but not of his <hi>Regall</hi> authority. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> by <hi>Heires,</hi> and <hi>Succeſſours</hi> are not underſtood <hi>Vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi> but ſuch onely as ſhall <hi>lawfully,</hi> and by right ſucceed: for as according to law,<note n="d" place="margin">Gloſſa <hi>in can</hi> Faciat <hi>22. q. 2</hi> &amp; leg. Vulgo <hi>f. de</hi> ſtatu homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num <hi>lib. 1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>we can onely doe that, which we can lawfully, and honestly doe,</hi> ſo in law, and conſcience they onely are reputed <hi>Heires,</hi> and
<hi>Succeſſours,</hi> who lawfully, and by right ſhall ſucceede. <hi>Lastly,</hi> by
<hi>Treaſons,</hi> and <hi>Traiterous Conspiracies</hi> are not underſtood <hi>impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> poſitive, <hi>or ſpirituall</hi> Treaſons, and which in regard chiefly of <hi>Religion</hi> are by the <hi>poſitive</hi> lawes onely of ſome <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> or <hi>Nations,</hi> but not of all made <hi>Treaſons,</hi> as are the comming in of Prieſts into this Realme ordained by the Popes authority <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But onely ſuch <hi>Treaſons</hi> are he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re underſtood, which are <hi>true,</hi> proper, and <hi>naturall</hi> Treaſons and which all <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> and <hi>Nations</hi> account for ſuch, as being repugnant to that <hi>Naturall,</hi> and <hi>civill</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">See above <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am. 3.</note> Allegiance, which all <hi>Subjects</hi> both Heathen, and Chriſtian by the law of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> doe owe to their lawfull <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne,</hi> whatſoever <hi>Religion</hi> He, or they ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="clause">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:4449:22"/>
            <head>The fourth Clauſe explained.</head>
            <p n="12">12 THE <hi>Fourth</hi> Clauſe, <hi>And I doe further ſweare,</hi> &amp;c. if it be rightly underſtood, is as cleare as the former. For therein, by <hi>force</hi> of the words, the
<hi>practiſe</hi> only of the <hi>Popes</hi> power to <hi>depoſe,</hi> or <hi>murther Princes,</hi> and the doctrine which maintaineth it for lawfull, to wit, <hi>That Princes, which be excommunicated, or deprived by the Pope, may,</hi> that is, by vertue of the <hi>Popes</hi> ſentence of <hi>Ecommunication,</hi> or <hi>Deprivation, bee depoſed, or murthered by their Subjects, or any other whatſoever,</hi> is abjured, I doe not ſay, as an <hi>hereſie,</hi> but as the words of this Clauſe are, <hi>as hereticall.</hi> For (as <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus Aragona,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aragona <hi>2</hi> a. <hi>2</hi> ae. q. <hi>11.</hi> ar.
<hi>2.</hi> Suarez diſp. <hi>19.</hi> de Fide. ſec. <hi>2.</hi> nam. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> and
<hi>Suarez,</hi> doe well obſerve) <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and an</hi> hereticall <hi>propoſition properly, and in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour are not the ſame, but doe differ as the</hi> act, <hi>or</hi> ſin,
<hi>and the</hi> matter <hi>thereof; becauſe</hi> hereſie <hi>properly doth ſignifie a certaine ſinne of infidelitie, but an</hi> hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <hi>propoſition doth onely ſignifie the</hi> matter <hi>of that ſinne: And therefore although</hi> pertinacie <hi>belongeth to the nature of</hi> hereſie, <hi>it doth not therefore follow, that it belongeth to the nature of an</hi> hereticall <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. I ſaid</hi> (ſaith <hi>Suarez</hi>) <hi>properly, and in rigour; for</hi> hereſie <hi>may alſo be distinguiſhed into</hi> materiall, and formall,
<hi>and ſo it may be ſaid, that an</hi> hereticall <hi>propoſition is a certaine</hi> hereſie, <hi>not</hi> formall, <hi>but</hi> materiall, <hi>and ſo it is not neceſſary,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4449:22"/>that it depend upon the</hi> pertinacie <hi>of the ſpeaker; for this only belongeth to</hi> formall <hi>hereſie, which is a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full act,</hi> and doth formally make an
<hi>Hereticke,</hi> as <hi>whiteneſſe</hi> doth formally make the ſubject, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is to be <hi>white. From whence it followeth</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aragona</hi>) <hi>that when Doctors call an</hi> hereticall <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition an</hi> Hereſie, <hi>they ſpeake not properly, becauſe it is not to be called an</hi> hereſie, <hi>but an</hi> hereticall <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</hi> For according to all <hi>Divines,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> S. Thom <hi>2</hi>a
<hi>2.</hi>e q. <hi>11.</hi> art. <hi>2.</hi> Cajet. Bannes, ibid. Aragona art. <hi>1.</hi> Suarez diſp. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9.</hi> de Fide ſec.
<hi>3.</hi>
               </note> to <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie,</hi> as it is a ſinne againſt <hi>Faith,</hi> and maketh a formall <hi>Heretike,</hi> is required <hi>pertinacie</hi> againſt the Doctrine, Declaration, and Senſe of the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13 Now ſuppoſing theſe <hi>two principles,</hi> which are ſo cleare and evident, as I have ſhewed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>, that no man of any reading, and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can deny either of them: <hi>the one,</hi> that it is a great controverſie among learned <hi>Catholikes,</hi> and a doctrine approved by many of them, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath not power to deprive
<hi>Princes</hi> of their <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> much leſſe of their <hi>Lives;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore truly <hi>probable,</hi> their approbation being not grounded upon any
<hi>principle,</hi> which is clearely falſe: <hi>The other,</hi> that <hi>a power, which is not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther certaine, but</hi> only <hi>probable,</hi> and in controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, <hi>can be no</hi> ſufficient <hi>ground to puniſh, depoſe,</hi> or <hi>deprive any man of any his right, and dominion,</hi> or of any other thing, <hi>which he poſſeſſeth;</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Doctor <hi>Kelliſon</hi> well inferreth, cannot be practiſed <hi>without open injuſtice:</hi> it cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly followeth, that this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4449:23"/>the <hi>practiſe</hi> of depoſing, or murdering <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> by the
<hi>Popes</hi> authoritie, and by <hi>vertue</hi> of his ſentence of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> or
<hi>Deprivation</hi> is manifeſtly <hi>falſe,</hi> as teaching <hi>open injustice,</hi> to wit,
<hi>Theft</hi> and <hi>Murder</hi> in a moſt high degree, and may therefore be abjured for ſuch, and conſequently for <hi>impious, damnable,</hi> indirectly, and by a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary conſequence repugnant to <hi>faith,</hi> and <hi>divine truth</hi> revealed in the holy Scriptures,<note n="h" place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale, Thou ſhalt not kill; Kill him not,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Caeſar,</hi> &amp;c. and in this ſenſe
<hi>hereticall,</hi> as the word <hi>[Hereticall]</hi> is uſually, and properly taken both by
<hi>Protestants,</hi> and alſo by the moſt part of Catholike <hi>Divines</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 26 M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. 21.</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>S</hi> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>2</hi> a. <hi>2</hi> a q.
<hi>1</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rt <hi>2.</hi> Baan. s &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagon ibid. Turrec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em. in Summa de Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. l. <hi>4.</hi> part. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> Director. Inquiſit. par. <hi>2.</hi> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. <hi>27.</hi> p. <hi>233.</hi> Canus, lib.
<hi>6.</hi> de l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lt. ad.
<hi>10.</hi> Scot in <hi>3.</hi> dist. <hi>35.</hi> Vulpes tom. <hi>1.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſp. <hi>2.</hi> art. <hi>5.</hi> &amp; diſp. <hi>3.</hi> art <hi>7</hi> Faber. q. <hi>1.</hi> Prologi, diſp. <hi>6.</hi> cap.
<hi>1.</hi> Caſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o lib. <hi>1.</hi> contr. hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cap. <hi>8.</hi> Vega li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.
<hi>9</hi> in Concil. Trid. cap. <hi>39.</hi> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c. a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>3.</hi> ſe t. diſt. <hi>23</hi> q
<hi>3.</hi> de hae eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. l. <hi>4</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. c. <hi>14.</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lina in part. <hi>1.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>2</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> p.
<hi>1.</hi> Vaſquez ibid. diſp. <hi>5</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> Faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolm ibid q. <hi>1.</hi> dub.
<hi>13.</hi>
               </note>, who hold, that the <hi>Church</hi> doth not make any doctrine to be
<hi>hereticall,</hi> or <hi>of Faith,</hi> but only <hi>declare</hi> it to be ſuch, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her <hi>declaration</hi> was truly ſuch, and that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is <hi>indirectly,</hi> ſecondarily, or by a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſequence repugnant <hi>to faith,</hi> is truly and properly <hi>hereticall,</hi> although hee that without <hi>pertinacie</hi> ſhould maintaine any ſuch doctrine in this ſenſe <hi>hereticall,</hi> before the <hi>Church</hi> hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared it to be ſuch, is not to be accounted an <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike,</hi> nor doth incurre <hi>Anathema,</hi> or any other penalties ordained againſt <hi>Heretikes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14 I ſaid above [<hi>their approbation being not grounded,</hi> &amp;c.] Becauſe the approbation of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,</hi> though they be never ſo many, if it be groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon any
<hi>principle, reaſon,</hi> or <hi>ſuppoſition,</hi> which is manifeſtly <hi>falſe,</hi> cannot make their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to be truly <hi>probable,</hi> to thoſe eſpecially (as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4449:23"/>
               <hi>Vaſquez</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Vaſq. <hi>1</hi> a. <hi>2</hi> ae aiſp. <hi>62</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi> ſect. Obſervan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum tamen m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xime est.</note> well obſerveth) who ſee the manifeſt
<hi>falſhood</hi> of that <hi>principle, reaſon,</hi> or <hi>ſuppoſition.</hi> As all thoſe <hi>Popes,</hi> and <hi>Doctors,</hi> who have approved, or doe approve the lawfull
<hi>practiſe</hi> of depoſing <hi>Princes</hi> by the <hi>Popes</hi> authority, <hi>either</hi> did, or doe thinke, and ſuppoſe, that it is moſt <hi>certaine,</hi> and of <hi>faith,</hi> nor in controverſie among learned <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes,</hi> that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath ſuch power to <hi>depoſe</hi> them, which all the world now ſeeth to be clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>falſe; or elſe</hi> they did not, or doe not conſider the difference betwixt meere
<hi>ſpeculation,</hi> and <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe,</hi> and betwixt a <hi>probable</hi> power to
<hi>favour,</hi> and to <hi>puniſh, depoſe,</hi> or <hi>diſpoſſeſſe;</hi> whereas all learned Catholikes, both <hi>Divines,</hi> and <hi>Lawyers</hi> doe agree in this manifeſt
<hi>principle,</hi> that a <hi>power, right,</hi> or <hi>title,</hi> which is not
<hi>certaine,</hi> but in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, is no ſufficient ground to <hi>deprive,</hi> or put any man out of his <hi>poſſeſsion,</hi> nor can be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed without <hi>open injustice,</hi> untill an undoubted Iudge, and whoſe authority for the determining of that matter is not queſtionable (as is the <hi>Popes</hi> authority to define undoubtedly matters of
<hi>faith</hi> without a Generall <hi>Councell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Beneath. num. 29.</note> as I will ſhew <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath</hi>) ſhall decide the queſtion.</p>
            <p n="15">15 I omit now <hi>two other</hi> Expoſitions of this Clauſe, and which ſome learned
<hi>Catholikes</hi> doe greatly applaud. <hi>The one</hi> of the Adverbe [as <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall</hi>] which being an Adverbe of <hi>ſimilitude,</hi> doth alwayes by <hi>force</hi> of the
<hi>word,</hi> ſignifie a <hi>ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude,</hi> and not a <hi>realitie,</hi> or
<hi>identitie,</hi> but onely in regard of the <hi>matter,</hi> to which it is applyed. So
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4449:24"/>that conſidering in <hi>penall</hi> lawes (as is this <hi>law</hi> for taking the <hi>Oath</hi>) all <hi>doubtfull</hi> words are ever to be taken in the more
<hi>favourable</hi> ſenſe, and which maketh the <hi>law</hi> to containe no
<hi>falſhood,</hi> or <hi>inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> they will have the ſenſe of this Clauſe to be this, <hi>I abjure this doctrine, and poſition as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall,</hi> that is, as having onely a
<hi>ſimilitude,</hi> and <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity</hi> with that doctrine and poſition, which is
<hi>hereticall.</hi> The other is of the <hi>Conjunction</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctive <hi>[or murthered]</hi> which according to the uſuall ſignification of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſpeech, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it immediately followeth the verb <hi>[may]</hi> implyeth a free choice to take which part of the <hi>Diſ-junction</hi> we pleaſe, and maketh not an <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute,</hi> but a
<hi>conditionall</hi> diſ-junctive propoſition, which, for as much as concerneth the
<hi>truth,</hi> or <hi>falſhood</hi> thereof, followeth the nature, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of a
<hi>copulative,</hi> and not of an <hi>abſolute,</hi> or common <hi>diſ-junctive</hi> propoſition. And it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the ſenſe of this Clauſe to be equivalent to this; <hi>I abjure as hereticall this doctrine, and poſition, That Princes, which be excommunicated, or depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the</hi> Pope, <hi>may be depoſed, and murthered by their Subjects:</hi> Which doctrine, and poſition in regard of the <hi>ſecond</hi> part, <hi>[and murthered]</hi> being by all Catholikes accounted <hi>hereticall,</hi> eſpecially ſeeing that <hi>murther</hi> is alwayes taken with us for an unjuſt, and wicked killing, and not for every <hi>killing,</hi> or
<hi>manſlaughter,</hi> the whole entire <hi>condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall</hi> diſ-junctive propoſition in regard only of this part may be truly abjured <hi>for hereticall.</hi> But
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4449:24"/>becauſe the <hi>Firſt</hi> Explication may abundantly ſuffice to make it apparant even to ſuch <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes,</hi> as are willing to take all the exceptions they can againſt any <hi>ambiguous</hi> word, or ſentence contained in the <hi>Oath,</hi> that not only the <hi>practiſe</hi> of <hi>murthering,</hi> or <hi>killing,</hi> but alſo of
<hi>depoſing</hi> Princes by the <hi>Popes</hi> authority, may be abjured <hi>for hereticall</hi> in a true, proper, and uſuall ſenſe, as I have ſhewed, without making him that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<hi>pertinacie</hi> ſhall maintaine it, to be <hi>properly</hi> an <hi>heretike,</hi> and alſo that theſe <hi>two later</hi> may bee ſeene more at large related, and confirmed by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.
<hi>Widdrington</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">In the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynder</hi> to the ſecond part of his
<hi>Confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of M. <hi>Fitz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herbert, per t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
               </note> againſt all the exceptions, which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Fitzherbert</hi> hath taken againſt them, it may ſuffice for this preſent onely to have tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched them thus briefly.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="clause">
            <head>The fifth Clauſe explained.</head>
            <p n="16">16 IN the <hi>Fifth</hi> Clauſe, <hi>And I doe beleeve,</hi> &amp;c. is not denied the
<hi>Popes</hi> power to <hi>abſolve</hi> from <hi>all Oaths, or any part thereof,</hi> becauſe there is not the ſame reaſon of <hi>this Oath,</hi> as there is of many other <hi>Oathes,</hi> which doe not concerne a <hi>third</hi> perſon, from which that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath power to
<hi>abſolve,</hi> or to <hi>diſpenſe</hi> in them, no <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike</hi> will deny. Neither is there in this Clauſe any other thing <hi>immediately</hi> ſworne, than that <hi>I doe beleeve,</hi> that is, not with <hi>divine</hi> and <hi>ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:4449:25"/>beleefe, but only with <hi>morall</hi> credulity, and <hi>humane</hi> perſwaſion, <hi>and in conſcience am reſolved, that neither the</hi> Pope, <hi>nor any other perſon hath power to abſolve me from this</hi> Oath, <hi>or any part ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,</hi> that is, can give mee leave and licence not to performe thoſe <hi>three things,</hi> which in the
<hi>Third</hi> Clauſe I promiſed to performe. For, according to the doctrine of all<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>See S.</hi> Thom. <hi>2</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>2</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> q. <hi>89</hi> ar. <hi>7.</hi> &amp;
<hi>9</hi> Cajec. ibid. Aragona art. <hi>3.7.</hi> &amp; <hi>9.</hi> Silveſter verbo juramentum,
<hi>1.</hi> qu. <hi>2</hi> &amp; jura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum <hi>5</hi> q <hi>2.</hi> Sotus lib <hi>8.</hi> de Iuſtitia, art. <hi>9.</hi> Vatentia, tom. <hi>3.</hi> diſp. <hi>6.</hi> queſt. <hi>7.</hi> punc. <hi>4.</hi> Sayrus lib. <hi>5.</hi> Theſauri, cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Divines, Abſolution,</hi> and <hi>Diſpenſation,</hi> hath not place in <hi>aſſertory</hi> Oaths, wherein ſome thing is affirmed, or denied, which, as ſoone as it is ſpoken, is immutably, and indiſpenſably true, or falſe, but only in <hi>promiſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> Oaths, wherein ſomething is <hi>promiſed</hi> to be done, or omitted. And to performe thoſe <hi>three things,</hi> although I had made no <hi>Oath,</hi> or <hi>promiſe</hi> to performe them, I am bound by the abſolute Law of GOD, and <hi>Nature</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">See above, num.
10.</note>, from which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Pope,</hi> nor any other <hi>Perſon</hi> hath power to
<hi>abſolve,</hi> or to <hi>diſpenſe</hi> therein.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="clause">
            <head>The ſixth Clauſe explained.</head>
            <p n="17">17 IN the <hi>Sixth</hi> Clauſe, <hi>Which I acknowledge,</hi> &amp;c. there is no other thing <hi>immediately</hi> ſworne, than my <hi>acknowledgement, that this</hi> Oath <hi>is lawfully miniſtred unto me by good, and full au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> which doubtleſſe I may lawfully
<hi>acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> and alſo <hi>ſweare,</hi> ſuppoſing it to be an <hi>Oath</hi> of true <hi>temporall</hi> Allegiance, and no <hi>falſhood, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:4449:25"/>or deniall of any true, <hi>ſpirituall</hi> obedience due to the
<hi>Popes</hi> Holineſſe to be contained there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Neither doe the <hi>King,</hi> and
<hi>Parliament</hi> take upon them in this <hi>Oath</hi> (as ſome doe ill inferre) the
<hi>Churches</hi> authority to <hi>define</hi> matters <hi>of faith,</hi> as what doctrine is
<hi>hereticall,</hi> and what <hi>Oath is lawfully miniſtred by good, and full authoritie:</hi> But only with the inward <hi>judgement</hi> of their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, (which, to diſtinguiſh from <hi>judgement</hi> of authoritie, or of a <hi>Iudge</hi> doing <hi>justice,</hi> is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally called <hi>judgement</hi> of <hi>diſcretion,</hi> and is nothing elſe than a <hi>right determining,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">S. Thom. <hi>1</hi>a. <hi>2</hi>ae. q. <hi>93.</hi> ar.
<hi>2.</hi> &amp; <hi>2</hi>a. <hi>2</hi>ae. qu. <hi>60</hi> art. <hi>1.</hi> Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Aragona, ec Salon, ibid. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus lib. <hi>3.</hi> de Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia, q. <hi>4.</hi> ar. <hi>1.</hi> Hurtadus diſt
<hi>7.</hi> de anima, ſect. <hi>2.</hi> paragr. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> or diſcerning <hi>of the underſtanding betwixt truth, and falſhood, good and evill in every matter either ſpeculative, or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall</hi>) they did determine, define, judge, and ſuppoſe the whole <hi>Oath,</hi> and every part thereof to be lawfull, and to containe no falſhood, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, but only a ſincere profeſſion of true <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall</hi> Allegiance, and that a <hi>temporal</hi> Prince hath good, and ful <hi>temporal</hi> authority to command the abjuring of any falſe, and
<hi>hereticall</hi> doctrine, if it be repugnant to this Allegiance, and thought ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the publike quiet of the Kingdome, whereof the <hi>Prince</hi> hath charge, and to forbid, and puniſh with <hi>temporall</hi> puniſhments, <hi>ſpirituall</hi> actions, as miniſtring of
<hi>Sacraments</hi> in a poiſoned matter, the publike maintaining of <hi>Hereſies;</hi> yea, of unneceſſary <hi>opinions,</hi> though they be <hi>probable</hi> in ſpeculation, if they be occaſion of <hi>Tumults,</hi> not as they are <hi>ſpirituall</hi> actions, but as they diſturbe the publike <hi>temporall</hi> peace, and in regard of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4449:26"/>
               <hi>temporall</hi> wrong done to the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> they become
<hi>temporall</hi> injuries. And upon this their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>judgement</hi> of diſcretion, and
<hi>determining</hi> of their underſtanding, which is agreeable to the grounds of
<hi>Catholike</hi> Religion,<note n="p" place="margin">See <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ellar.</hi> lib 5. de Rom. <hi>Pont</hi> cap. 7.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>quinta ratione</hi> loan. <hi>Paris.</hi> de poteſt. Reg <hi>&amp; Pag.</hi> cap. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d 37 <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tus.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n 4
<hi>diſt.</hi> 29. q. 1. ar. 4. <hi>Victoria</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lict. 1. de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt. Eccle. ſec. 7. <hi>paragr.</hi> oct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> propoſitio.
<hi>Pannes</hi> 2<hi>a.</hi> 2<hi>ae.</hi> q. 11 at. 4. q 1. in fine, <hi>Aragon.</hi> ibid.</note> they thought it requiſite for the <hi>publike peace</hi> of the Kingdom, for maintaining the
<hi>Kings</hi> temporal <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> and to prevent the danger of future
<hi>Conſpiracies</hi> like to that of the <hi>Powder-Treaſon,</hi> to ordaine this <hi>new Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and to binde all the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> of the Realme under the penalty of a <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire</hi> to take the ſame, which doubtleſſe, as I ſaid, the
<hi>King,</hi> and <hi>State</hi> have good, and full au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to doe, ſuppoſing it to be an
<hi>Oath</hi> of true <hi>temporall</hi> Allegiance, and no falſhood, or injuſtice to be contained therein. Neither doe thoſe words [<hi>and do renounce all Pardons</hi> &amp;c.] imply a renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of all <hi>Pardons,</hi> and <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> in generall, but onely of ſuch, which ſhall <hi>diſpenſe</hi> with me, or give me leave to doe contrary to that which I promiſed in the <hi>Third</hi> Clauſe, <hi>to beare faith, and true Allegiance to his Majeſtie</hi> &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="clause">
            <head>The ſeventh Clauſe explained.</head>
            <p n="18">18 THe plaine meaning of the <hi>Seventh</hi> Clauſe, <hi>And all theſe things</hi> &amp;c. is, that I muſt uſe no fraude, or guile, but <hi>plainly, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely acknowledge</hi> all the former things, and alſo
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:4449:26"/>
               <hi>ſweare</hi> them all, either <hi>immediately,</hi> or <hi>mediatly,</hi> according as the <hi>expreſſe words</hi> of every Clauſe, and <hi>the plaine, and common ſenſe, and understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame words</hi> ſhall import, <hi>without any equivocation, mentall evaſion, or ſecret reſervation whatſoever;</hi> that is, I muſt neither <hi>equivocate,</hi> or uſe <hi>equivocation,</hi> which is to ſpeake
<hi>equivocall</hi> words, or which have diverſe ſignifications, not in that ſenſe, wherein the hearer, or <hi>Law-maker</hi> doth, or ought in reaſon to underſtand them: nor uſe
<hi>mentall,</hi> or <hi>ſecret reſervation,</hi> that is to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve</hi> in my minde ſome hidden, and <hi>inward</hi> ſenſe, which the <hi>outward</hi> words by me ſpoken, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their impoſition, and the common under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of them, all circumſtances conſidered, cannot ſignifie to others. As if one being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, whether he ever heard
<hi>Peter</hi> ſpeake ſuch words, ſhould anſwer. that he never heard him ſpeake ſuch words, reſerving in his minde, <hi>in the Tower of London,</hi> or the like: which
<hi>inward,</hi> ſecret, and <hi>reſerved</hi> ſenſe thoſe <hi>outward</hi> words, cannot ſignifie to others. And therefore this <hi>mentall reſervation</hi> (howſoever the
<hi>ſpeaker</hi> in his <hi>minde,</hi> which is unknowne to others, intendeth to make a
<hi>Chimericall</hi> mixture, and union of the <hi>reſerved</hi> ſenſe, and the
<hi>outward</hi> words) is nothing elſe then a flat, and formall <hi>Lie,</hi> as to <hi>Lie</hi> is taken, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined by Saint <hi>Austin,</hi> and other Divines.<note place="margin">S.
<hi>Aug.</hi> lib 1. de <hi>Meadacio</hi> cap. 3 S. <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m</hi> 2<hi>a</hi> 2<hi>e.</hi> q 110 See S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> beneath<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nu.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3</note> So that know, whether I am bound to
<hi>ſweare</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately every thing contained in any clauſe, or onely my ſincere
<hi>acknowledgement, declaration, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4449:27"/>or reſolution</hi> of that thing, I muſt regard the <hi>expreſſe words</hi> of every Clauſe, and in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they binde me, either to <hi>ſweare</hi> the thing <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately,</hi> or onely my ſincere <hi>acknowledgement</hi> &amp;c. thereof.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="clause">
            <head>The eight Clauſe explained.</head>
            <p n="19">19 THe <hi>laſt</hi> Clauſe, <hi>And I doe make</hi> &amp;c. hath in it no difficulty, ſuppoſing the <hi>Oath</hi> to be lawfull, and <hi>commanded</hi> by good and full authority: for that every good <hi>Subject</hi> is bound to obey the <hi>constitutive</hi> precept of his lawfull <hi>Superiour</hi> in that manner as I will ſhew beneath,<note n="q" place="margin">num. 26.</note> 
               <hi>heartily, willingly, and truely,</hi> that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faignedly, not onely for <hi>wroth,</hi> or feare of <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as the wicked doe, but for conſcience, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and vertue<note n="r" place="margin">See <hi>Vaſquez</hi> 1<hi>a</hi>
2<hi>ae. disp.</hi> 51. cap 3. <hi>&amp; disp</hi> 73. cap. 7. <hi>&amp; disp.</hi> 86. cap.
5.</note> ſake.</p>
            <p>Five <hi>generall</hi> obſervations <hi>for the better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, how all the chiefe</hi> objections, <hi>which are uſually made againſt the</hi> Oath <hi>in generall, may bee eaſily anſwered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20 HAving explained all the clauſes of the <hi>Oath</hi> in that briefe, and perſpicuous manner as you have ſeene, whereby any prudent man may eaſily anſwere all the chiefe <hi>objections,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:4449:27"/>which are commonly made againſt any <hi>Clauſe</hi> thereof in
<hi>particular,</hi> I thinke it not amiſſe to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexe hereunto <hi>five</hi> generall
<hi>obſervations</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>doubtfull</hi> words, <hi>Perjuries,</hi> the
<hi>Popes</hi> Breves, <hi>Scandall,</hi> and the <hi>ſafer</hi> way, whereby all the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall
<hi>arguments,</hi> which are uſually urged againſt the <hi>Oath</hi> in generall, may alſo according to the grounds of <hi>Catholike</hi> Religion be clearely confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For againſt the
<hi>Oath</hi> in <hi>generall</hi> it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly objected, <hi>Firſt,</hi> that there are contained in the <hi>Oath</hi> diverſe ambiguous, and <hi>doubtfull</hi> ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which may have a <hi>double</hi> ſignification, good and bad, true and falſe, which therefore being ſo
<hi>doubtfull</hi> cannot bee abſolutely ſworne without danger of <hi>Perjury</hi> 2. That the
<hi>Popes</hi> Holineſſe our ſupreme <hi>ſpirituall</hi> Paſtour; whoſe voice we are bound to heare, and follow, hath by his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves forbidden the <hi>Oath,</hi> as <hi>containing many things flat contrary to faith, and ſalvation.</hi> 3. That to take the <hi>Oath</hi> is no ſmall <hi>ſcandall</hi> to the <hi>weaker</hi> ſort of <hi>Catholikes,</hi> which our
<hi>Saviour</hi> in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell<note n="f" place="margin">Matth. 18.</note> with a fearefull curſe, and <hi>woe be to that man by whom ſcandall commeth,</hi> commandeth us to avoid.
<hi>Lastly,</hi> that to refuſe the <hi>Oath</hi> is the <hi>more ſafe,</hi> and the more
<hi>probable opinion,</hi> which every man in thoſe things, which are dangerous to the health of the <hi>body,</hi> much more of the <hi>ſoule,</hi> ought in wiſedome to preferre before that, which is the <hi>leſſe ſafe,</hi> and the <hi>leſſe probable.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="observation">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:4449:28"/>
            <head>The firſt Obſervation.</head>
            <p n="21">21 FIrſt therefore concerning <hi>doubtfull</hi> words it is to be <hi>obſerved,</hi> that in <hi>penall</hi> lawes (as is this for taking the <hi>Oath</hi> commanded by Act of
<hi>Parlament</hi> under the penalty of a <hi>Praemunire</hi>) all <hi>doubtfull</hi> words, which have diverſe ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons not <hi>improper,</hi> nor <hi>unuſuall,</hi> are alwaies to be taken in the more <hi>favourable</hi> ſenſe, and which may make the <hi>law</hi> to be juſt, and reaſonable, and not to be drawne to a <hi>falſe,</hi> odious, and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient ſenſe, and which maketh the <hi>law</hi> to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt. And this is the common Doctrine of
<hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines,</hi> and <hi>Lawyers,</hi> and agreeable both to the <hi>Canonicall,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>can.</hi> Cum tu de testibus <hi>c. 16 can.</hi> Ad no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stram <hi>de</hi> Iure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurando <hi>cap. 21</hi> &amp; <hi>de</hi> Regulis Iuris <hi>in</hi> Sexio. <hi>reg. 49</hi> In. pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</note> and <hi>Civill</hi> law. For <hi>lawes are to be</hi> expounded more favourably (ſaith the <hi>civill</hi> law<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>leg.</hi> Benigai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, ff. <hi>de</hi> legibus.</note>) <hi>that the will,</hi> or meaning of them may be conſerved. And <hi>in a doubtfull, or ambiguous word of the law, that ſenſe is rather to be choſen,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>leg.</hi> In Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigua, ff. <hi>de</hi> le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus.</note> 
               <hi>which is void of all default, eſpecially ſeeing that the will alſo, or meaning of the law may hereby be gathered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="22">22 Yea, which is more, according to <hi>Suarez, if at any time the property of the words ſhould induce any injustice, or like abſurdity concerning the minde,</hi> or meaning <hi>of the Law-maker,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quarez</hi> lib. 6. de <hi>legibus</hi> cap. 1</note>
               <hi>they muſt be drawne to a ſenſe alſo improper, wherein the law may be juſt, and reaſonable, for this is preſumed to be the minde of the Law-maker, as it hath been declared by many
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:4449:28"/>lawes in</hi> ff. <hi>tit. de Legibus.</hi> Thus <hi>Suarez.</hi> Wherby it is evident, that what words ſoever in this <hi>Oath</hi> may be <hi>doubtfull,</hi> and have diverſe ſignifications, eſpecially not <hi>improper,</hi> nor <hi>unuſuall,</hi> as <hi>I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge before God, I beleeve, Succeſſours, Treaſons, as hereticall, or murthered,</hi> or any other whatſoever, we ought to expound them in the more <hi>favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> ſenſe, and which may make the <hi>Oath,</hi> and the <hi>meaning</hi> of the <hi>Law-maker</hi> to be juſt, and reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and not to draw, much leſſe to wreſt them to a <hi>falſe,</hi> odious, and inconvenient ſenſe, and wherein we will needs make the <hi>Oath</hi> to be in our judgement unreaſonable, and wicked.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="observation">
            <head>The ſecond Obſervation.</head>
            <p n="23">23 <hi>SEcondly</hi> concerning <hi>Perjurie</hi> it is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that
<hi>Perjurie</hi> ſpeaking properly (for ſometimes it is taken for every unlawful, and idle
<hi>ſwearing,</hi> although it want not <hi>verity,</hi> the firſt, and chiefe companion of an
<hi>Oath</hi>) is defined by <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines,</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Magiſter</hi> in 3.
<hi>diſt.</hi> 29. S. <hi>Thom.</hi> 2<hi>a.</hi> 2<hi>ae.</hi> q. 98. ar. 1. <hi>&amp; Theologi</hi> ibid.</note> to be <hi>a Lie confirmed by Oath.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as a <hi>Lie</hi> is divided into a <hi>materiall Lie,</hi> when one ſpeaketh as he reaſonably thinketh, and yet in very deede it is otherwiſe, and into a <hi>formall Lie,</hi> when one affirmeth that to be true, which he thinketh to be falſe, or contrary wiſe, for <hi>to Lie</hi> (ſaith Saint
<hi>Austin</hi>) <hi>is to ſpeake againſt the minde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. <hi>Aug.</hi> lib. 1. de <hi>Mendacio</hi> c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>or to have one thing in the minde, and to affirme an
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:4449:29"/>other by words, or any other ſignes;</hi> So <hi>Periurie</hi> is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into <hi>matertall,</hi> and <hi>formall Periurie,</hi> for that <hi>Periurie</hi> is nothing elſe then a <hi>Lie confirmed by Oath,</hi> and onely addeth to a <hi>Lie</hi> the calling of
<hi>God</hi> to witneſſe of what is ſpoken. Wherefore as it is unlawfull for one to affirme that to be <hi>true,</hi> which he knoweth to be <hi>falſe,</hi> or contrariwiſe, for this were expreſly, and formally to <hi>Lie,</hi> or to affirme that to be <hi>true,</hi> whereof he is
<hi>ignorant,</hi> or <hi>doubtfull,</hi> for this were to expoſe himſelfe to <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> of being <hi>forſworne,</hi> and <hi>he that loveth danger ſhall periſh therein,</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.</note> So alſo it is much more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull to confirme the ſame by <hi>Oath,</hi> whereby he maketh <hi>God,</hi> who is <hi>Truth</hi> it ſelfe, either the
<hi>Patron</hi> of a <hi>Lie,</hi> or to be ignorant of the <hi>truth.</hi> So that whatſoever may bee affirmed, or denyed without danger of <hi>Lying,</hi> may alſo bee ſworne without danger of <hi>Periurie,</hi> And as the <hi>falſhood,</hi> which maketh a <hi>formall Lie,</hi> is not to bee taken from the thing as it is in it ſelfe, or <hi>à parte rei,</hi> but as it is in the <hi>minde</hi> of the <hi>ſpeaker,</hi> for that <hi>to Lie is to ſpeake againſt the minde,</hi> ſo the <hi>falſhood,</hi> which maketh <hi>formall Periurie,</hi> is not to bee taken from the thing as it is in it ſelfe, or <hi>ex parte rei,</hi> but as it is againſt the minde, and knowledge of the <hi>ſwearer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">24 Wherefore in all <hi>Oathes,</hi> as well <hi>promiſſorie,</hi> as
<hi>aſſertorie,</hi> to avoid the ſinne of <hi>Periurie,</hi> Truth is alwaies required. In a
<hi>promiſſorie</hi> two fold <hi>truth</hi> is neceſſarie, <hi>One</hi> for the
<hi>preſent,</hi> that the <hi>words</hi> outwardly ſpoken bee agreeable to the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4449:29"/>
               <hi>mind,</hi> and that therefore the <hi>ſwearer</hi> have for the preſent a <hi>minde,</hi> or purpoſe to performe what he promiſeth; <hi>the other</hi> for the
<hi>future,</hi> that he verily thinke, the thing which he promiſeth he is able, and may lawfully perform, and that for as much as lieth in him, at the time appointed he performe the ſame. But the <hi>truth,</hi> which is required to an <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertorie</hi> Oath, conſiſteth in this (ſaith <hi>Gregorius de Valentia,</hi> and <hi>Sayrus</hi>) that <hi>the thing be true,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Valentia</hi> tom. 3. <hi>disp.</hi> 6. q. 7 <hi>pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c.</hi> 3. <hi>Sayrus</hi> lib. 1 <hi>Theſauri</hi> cap. 4. num. 7.
<hi>Azor.</hi> tom. 1. <hi>Iuſtitut</hi> lib. 11. cap. 2. q. 5. <hi>Sauchiz</hi> lib. 3. in
<hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>calogum</hi> cap. 4. num. 10.</note>
               <hi>at least wiſe according to the reaſonable judgement of the ſwearer.</hi> And <hi>to the truth of an aſſertory</hi> Oath (ſaith <hi>Azorius,</hi> and <hi>Sauchiz</hi>) <hi>it is required, and ſufficeth, that the ſwearer thinke it to be ſo prudently, and not moved by light, or ſlender, but by aſſured, and likely or probable conjecture, and therefore according to the ſwearers judgment agreeable to reaſon, whether the thing be in very deede,</hi> or
<hi>ex parte rei, true, or falſe, for this</hi> (ſaith <hi>Sauchiz</hi>) <hi>is to be morally certaine.</hi> The like hath <hi>Silveſter, Sotus, Arag. and Suarez.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Silv. verbo Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurium</hi> q. 1. <hi>Sot.</hi> l. 8 <hi>de Iuſtitia</hi> q. 2. ar. 3. <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gona</hi> 2<hi>a.</hi> 2<hi>ae.</hi> q. 89. ar. 3. <hi>Suar.</hi> tom 2. de
<hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig.</hi> l. 3.3. c. 5.</note> And if <hi>morall</hi> certainty, or <hi>reaſonable</hi> aſſurance were not ſufficient to excuſe from <hi>Perjurie,</hi> no man could lawfully
<hi>ſweare,</hi> or acknowledge by <hi>Oath,</hi> any <hi>King</hi> whatſoever, to be a true and lawful <hi>King,</hi> or any <hi>Biſhop</hi> whatſoever to be a true, and lawfull
<hi>Biſhop,</hi> becauſe of theſe, and all ſuch like, we can have but <hi>moral</hi> certaintie, or <hi>reaſonable</hi> aſſurance.</p>
            <p n="25">25 And by this it is evident, that albeit there may bee brought ſome <hi>probable</hi> arguments to ſhew, that diverſe words, and ſentences contained in the <hi>Oath,</hi> being conſidered barely by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and without due circumſtances, may be
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:4449:30"/>
               <hi>doubtfull,</hi> and ambiguous, that is, not cleare, and morally certaine, and ſo for one to <hi>ſweare</hi> them in that <hi>doubtfull</hi> ſenſe, were to expoſe himſelfe to danger of <hi>perjury,</hi> yet conſidering, as I ſhewed above<note n="a" place="margin">num. 21.22.</note>, ſuch <hi>doubtfull</hi> words are to be taken in the more
<hi>favourable</hi> ſenſe, and which maketh the <hi>Law</hi> to be juſt and reaſonable, and to containe no <hi>falſhood,</hi> or <hi>injuſtice,</hi> all danger of <hi>Perjury</hi> is avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereby. For albeit there be danger of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury</hi> to ſweare <hi>doubtfull</hi> words in a <hi>doubtful</hi> ſenſe, yet to ſweare words which of themſelves are
<hi>doubtfull</hi> in a <hi>true,</hi> and determinate ſenſe, and wherein they are not
<hi>doubtfull,</hi> but cleare, and morally <hi>certaine,</hi> there is no danger of
<hi>Perjury.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="observation">
            <head>The third Obſervation.</head>
            <p n="26">26 THirdly,<note place="margin">Hugolin. par. <hi>2.</hi> de Cenſuris, c. <hi>6.</hi> in prins.</note> concerning the <hi>Popes Breves,</hi> which (as <hi>Hugolinus</hi> noteth) <hi>are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe,</hi> than the <hi>Popes letters made by his Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, and ſealed by the</hi> Pope <hi>in red wax with the</hi> Fiſhers <hi>Ring, and have the ſame force, which have the</hi> Popes <hi>Reſcripts,</hi> or his Letters written in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to other letters, <hi>and are therefore called</hi> Breves,<note place="margin">Rebuſſius in praxi benefic. part.
<hi>3.</hi> nu. <hi>4.</hi> Archidiaconus, &amp; Geminianus in cap. Quis
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſciat. diſt. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>becauſe they are written</hi> briefly, <hi>and in few words:</hi> whe reas the <hi>Popes Buls</hi> are ſo called (as <hi>Petrus Rebaffius,</hi> and others obſerve) <hi>for that they are ſigned with a round tablet of lead, wherein the pictures of</hi> Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> are <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven.</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:4449:30"/>Wee muſt obſerve firſt of all the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt a
<hi>declarative,</hi> and a <hi>conſtitutive</hi> Law, or precept. For a <hi>conſtitutive</hi> precept doth make the thing which it forbiddeth, to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, which otherwiſe would bee lawfull, as is the <hi>precept</hi> to abſtaine from <hi>fleſh</hi> in time of <hi>Lent,</hi> and from <hi>ſervile</hi> workes upon <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes,</hi> and commanded <hi>Holy-dayes:</hi> And this <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> eſpecially <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> abſtracting from
<hi>ſcandall,</hi> and <hi>contempt,</hi> which are forbidden by the Law of GOD, and
<hi>Nature,</hi> doth ſeldome, or never binde with danger<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Salas diſp. <hi>11.</hi> de leg. ſect. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>death,</hi> or any other great <hi>corporall,</hi> or <hi>temporall</hi> harme; and moreover it muſt be obeyed ſo long as it is not <hi>manifeſtly unjust</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Vaſq. tom <hi>2.</hi> in Iam.
<hi>2</hi>ae diſp. <hi>151.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi> in fin. Suar tom. <hi>5.</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>3.</hi> part. diſp. <hi>4</hi> ſect.
<hi>6.</hi> nu. <hi>5.</hi> &amp; lib. <hi>1.</hi> de leg. c. <hi>9.</hi> nu. <hi>9.</hi> Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia tom. <hi>3.</hi> punc. <hi>2</hi> Sayrus lib. <hi>1.</hi> Theſauri, c. <hi>12.</hi> Salas diſp.
<hi>10.</hi> de leg ſect. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>, nor in <hi>prejudice</hi> of a <hi>third</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon<note n="d" place="margin">See Beneath num 31.</note>, neither is it ſufficient, that it have onely a <hi>probable</hi> ſhew of injuſtice. For, as Doctor <hi>Kelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">In his <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe</hi> of the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> and <hi>Priace</hi> &amp;c <hi>cap.</hi> 15 <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 74</note> well inferreth from
<hi>Vaſquez</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Vaſqu. <hi>1</hi>a. <hi>2</hi>ae diſp <hi>62.</hi> nu. <hi>3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> doctrine (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he doth not wel apply it to the <hi>Popes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarative <hi>Breves</hi>) <hi>every Subject is bound to obey his lawfull Superiours commandement,</hi> to wit, <hi>conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, when he commandeth according to a</hi> probable <hi>opinion, though he command a thing, which is againſt the Subjects opinion, and that alſo</hi> probable, <hi>becauſe the Subject may follow any mans</hi> probable <hi>opinion, and conſequently his Superiours, that alſo being</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, <hi>and if he may, he muſt, becauſe his Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our commandeth.</hi> And the reaſon is, becauſe all the obligation of this <hi>precept</hi> dependeth chiefly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>will</hi> and <hi>authority</hi> of the <hi>Superiour,</hi> who is in poſſeſſion of his authority, ſo long as it is not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4449:31"/>
               <hi>doubtfull,</hi> or queſtionable, and the thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded be not
<hi>manifeſtly unjuſt,</hi> nor in <hi>prejudice</hi> of a <hi>third</hi> perſon, who alſo is in poſſeſſion of his good name, and goods, which cannot be juſtly taken from him under pretence of a meere <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable</hi> authority, right, or title.</p>
            <p n="27">27 But a <hi>declarative</hi> precept doth not make, but only <hi>declare,</hi> and ſuppoſe the thing which it forbiddeth, to be otherwiſe unlawfull, as being forbidden by ſome <hi>former</hi> law, as are the <hi>lawes</hi> of <hi>Princes</hi> made againſt <hi>Theft, murder, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> or the like, which are otherwiſe forbidden by the Law of GOD, and
<hi>Nature.</hi> And all the obligation of this precept,<note place="margin">Suarez lib. <hi>3.</hi> de leg. cap. <hi>14.</hi> &amp; cap. <hi>20.</hi> nu. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Suarez</hi> well obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, doth depend upon the <hi>reaſon,</hi> and <hi>ſuppoſition,</hi> for which this
<hi>declarative</hi> precept is impoſed, and upon the <hi>obligation</hi> of the former
<hi>Law,</hi> which this precept doth ſuppoſe, and declare. So that if the <hi>reaſon,</hi> and <hi>ſuppoſition,</hi> for which this <hi>decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative</hi> precept is impoſed, be not true, and that there be no ſuch <hi>precedent</hi> law, or prohibition, which the
<hi>declarative</hi> precept doth ſuppoſe, and <hi>declare,</hi> the <hi>declarative</hi> precept hath no force to binde at all. And if the <hi>precept</hi> be ſometimes <hi>mixt,</hi> that is, in part <hi>declarative,</hi> and in part <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutive,</hi> it muſt in part, as it is ſuch, participate the nature, and conditions of them both.</p>
            <p n="28">28 <hi>Secondly,</hi> we muſt obſerve, that the <hi>Popes Breves,</hi> forbidding
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Catholikes to take the <hi>Oath,</hi> doe not <hi>conſtitute</hi> a new law, or make the <hi>Oath</hi> to bee unlawfull, but they doe onely
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:4449:31"/>ſuppoſe, and <hi>declare</hi> it to be otherwiſe unlawfull, and forbidden by the <hi>Law</hi> of GOD, for that <hi>it containeth many things</hi> (ſay the <hi>Breves</hi>)
<hi>which are clearely repugnant to faith, and ſalvation.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe his
<hi>declarative. Breves</hi> are grounded upon <hi>falſe</hi> reaſons, and ſuppoſitions, to wit, upon the <hi>Popes</hi> opinion, and of ſome other his <hi>Divines,</hi> eſpecially Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> that either his power to <hi>excommunicate,</hi> to <hi>binde,</hi> and <hi>looſe</hi> in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, to <hi>abſolve</hi> from <hi>Oaths</hi> in generall, is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denied in the <hi>Oath,</hi> which is manifeſtly falſe, <hi>or elſe</hi> that his power to depoſe <hi>Princes,</hi> which is plainly denied in the <hi>Oath,</hi> is moſt
<hi>certaine,</hi> and <hi>of faith,</hi> nor diſproved by many learned <hi>Catholikes,</hi> which all the World now ſeeth to be no leſſe clearely untrue, it is evident, according to
<hi>Suarez</hi> doctrine, and manifeſt reaſon, that <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes are not bound to obſerve them. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unleſſe one at leaſt-wiſe, I doe not ſay
<hi>proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> argument (for this is not ſufficient to <hi>demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate</hi> a matter
<hi>of faith,</hi> and the <hi>Oath</hi> to be <hi>plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repugnant to faith, and ſalvation</hi>) but cleare, and <hi>convincing</hi> can be brought, which no man hath hitherto, nor can in my judgement produce to prove ſome one thing in the <hi>Oath</hi> to be contrary to
<hi>faith,</hi> or <hi>ſalvation,</hi> that <hi>Engliſh</hi> Catholikes are bound to obey the ſaid <hi>declarative Breves,</hi> being grounded upon <hi>falſe</hi> reaſons, and ſuppoſitions, no man of any learning, or judgement can ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, and from his heart affirme.</p>
            <p n="29">29 To ſay, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath by his <hi>Breves</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:4449:32"/>defined <hi>ex Cathedra</hi> the <hi>Oath</hi> to be unlawfull, and to
<hi>containe many things flat contrary to faith, and ſalvation,</hi> is not only moſt clearely untrue, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to little purpoſe though it were true: <hi>firſt,</hi> for that they want thoſe conditions, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Canus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Canus lib. <hi>5.</hi> de locis, ca. <hi>5.</hi> q. <hi>4.</hi> Bellar. lib. <hi>4.</hi> de Rom. Pont. c. <hi>4.</hi> &amp;
<hi>5.</hi> &amp; lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Concil. c. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Divines</hi> (who hold that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to define infallibly matters <hi>of faith</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>Generall Councell</hi>) are required to a defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<hi>ex Cathedra,</hi> among which this is one, that they muſt be directed to the <hi>whole Church,</hi> and not onely to ſome <hi>particular Churches,</hi> or <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes;</hi> for which cauſe they are well called by <hi>Ioannes Eudeamon</hi> a learned <hi>Ieſuite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioan. Eudaemon in Praefat. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallelli Torti.</note> the <hi>Popes pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Letters to the Engliſh Catholikes,</hi> and beſides it were a ſtrange definition <hi>ex Cathedra,</hi> wherein no one particular propoſition among ſo many is expreſſed: <hi>Secondly,</hi> for that although they did containe a definition <hi>ex Cathedra,</hi> yet conſidering that it is a very <hi>probable</hi> doctrine, it being appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by ſo many excellent <hi>Divines</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Patres Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilii Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis, &amp; Baſil. Had<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ionus Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa in q. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm. Card. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merac in Tract. de authorie Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae. Card. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanus, lib. <hi>2.</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>concord. Cath. cap. ult. Card. Florent. in cap. Significaſti de elect. Card. Pa orm. ibid. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buleniſis in c. <hi>18.</hi> Matth q. <hi>108</hi> &amp; in Defenſorio, part. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>69.</hi> Ioan. Pariſ. Gerſon, Major, Almainus, &amp; Doctores Pariſienſes communiter. Victoria in Rolect. de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. Papae propoſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>3</hi>a. Navar in c. Novit de Iudiciis notab. <hi>3.</hi> num <hi>84. who hold this opinion to bee</hi> probable.</note>, and
<hi>Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> that the <hi>Keyes</hi> were given <hi>principally</hi> to the
<hi>Church,</hi> and to Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> as he repreſented the <hi>Church,</hi> and that the
<hi>Pope</hi> cannot define any thing to be <hi>of faith</hi> certainly, and undoubtedly without a
<hi>Generall Councell,</hi> to which according to theſe <hi>Doctors</hi> he is ſubject, and not ſuperiour, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:4449:32"/>ſequently that his <hi>definitions</hi> can be no <hi>infallible,</hi> and
<hi>undoubted</hi> ground of <hi>Catholike faith,</hi> it clearely followeth, that no
<hi>Catholike</hi> is bound to give more credit to his <hi>definition</hi> in this point, that to his doctrine, and opinion, which is <hi>not certaine,</hi> but only <hi>probable.</hi> And therefore when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the <hi>Pope</hi> defineth any doctrine to be <hi>of faith,</hi> which indeed is <hi>Catholike</hi> doctrine, and <hi>of faith,</hi> we muſt not beleeve with
<hi>Catholike faith</hi> that doctrine to be <hi>Catholike,</hi> and <hi>of faith,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Pope</hi> hath <hi>defined</hi> it (for ſo wee ſhould build our <hi>faith</hi> upon a
<hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>ground,</hi> which is not <hi>certaine</hi> to all learned
<hi>Catholikes,</hi> but uncertaine, and fallible) but becauſe the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> which is <hi>the pillar, and ground of truth</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Tim. 3.</hi> Sotus de ſecret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tegendo memb. <hi>3.</hi> q.
<hi>2.</hi> in Reſp. ad <hi>1</hi> m.</note> hath by expreſſe, or tacite conſent approved, and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it for ſuch.</p>
            <p n="30">30 Moreover, as <hi>Dominicus Sotus</hi> doth well obſerve (whoſe doctrine in this point is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the <hi>Canon law,</hi> and the <hi>Expoſitours</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of)
<hi>Prelates, and Iudges are not in poſſeſsion in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their Subjects, but ſo far forth as they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand things that are just, and therefore when it is doubtfull, whether they command that which is juſt, then if it be inprejudice of a</hi> third <hi>perſon, becauſe that</hi> third <hi>perſon is alſo in poſſeſsion of his good name, and goods, the Subject doth nothing againſt obedience, if he require of his Prelate a reaſon of his commandement, propounding humbly the reaſons of his doubt.</hi> Wherefore Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the third in his <hi>Letters,</hi> or <hi>Breves</hi> the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venna,</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:4449:33"/>giveth him this leſſon,<note n="i" place="margin">In c. Si quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do de Reſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note> that conſidering deligently the quality of the buſineſſe, he either reverently fulfill his commandement, or by his letters pretend a reaſonable cauſe, why he cannot fulfill it. Whereupon all the <hi>Expoſitours</hi> of the <hi>Canon Law,</hi> who expound this <hi>Canon,</hi> doe give this generall rule,<note n="k" place="margin">Gloſſa Ioan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Andreas, Panomitan. Petrus Ancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranus, Felinus, and others.</note> that the Superiours com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement ought either to be fulfilled, or a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon yeelded, why it is not fulfilled.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Seeing therfore that Engliſh <hi>Catholikes,</hi> as it is well knowne and publike to the whole world, have moſt humbly propounded, and yeelded to <hi>His Holineſſe</hi> the reaſons, for which they are <hi>doubtfull,</hi> or rather without any <hi>doubt</hi> are fully perſwaded, that his <hi>declarative Breves</hi> forbidding them to take the <hi>Oath,</hi> are unjuſt, and grounded upon <hi>falſe</hi> reaſons, and ſuppoſitions, and alſo
<hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiciall</hi> to themſelves, and to the <hi>Kings</hi> Majeſtie, it is evident, that with ſuch manifeſt danger of their owne <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> and <hi>temporall</hi> ruine, and ſo great prejudice to the <hi>Kings</hi> ſupreme authority in temporalls, they are not bound to obey them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their <hi>Princes</hi> commandement, eſpecially ſeeing that his commandement to take the <hi>Oath,</hi> going before the <hi>Popes</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement to refuſe it, muſt, as I ſaid above,<note n="l" place="margin">num. 26.</note> be obeied, ſo long as no one <hi>Clauſe</hi> of the <hi>Oath</hi> can be cleerely <hi>convinced</hi> to be unlawfull. And although no <hi>inferiour</hi> may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, and judge his <hi>Superiours</hi> commandment with
<hi>judgement</hi> of <hi>authority,</hi> which ſuppoſeth a <hi>Superiority</hi> over the perſon, whoſe actions are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:4449:33"/>and judged, yet that with <hi>judgement</hi> of <hi>diſcretion,</hi> which is the <hi>inward</hi> guide, and rule of every mans <hi>conſcience,</hi> every <hi>Subject</hi> may examine, and judge his <hi>Superiours</hi> commandements, and conſequently the <hi>Popes</hi> Breves whether they be juſt, or unjuſt, conſtitutive, or declarative, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of a
<hi>third</hi> perſon, or not in prejudice, and upon what reaſons, and ſuppoſitions they are grounded, no man that hath any judgement can deny.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="observation">
            <head>The fourth Obſervation.</head>
            <p n="32">32 <hi>FOurthly</hi> concerning <hi>Scandall</hi> it is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that there are
<hi>two</hi> ſorts of <hi>Scandall,</hi> the <hi>one</hi> is called <hi>active,</hi> or given, the <hi>other, paſsive,</hi> taken, or received, and they are ſignified in the holy
<hi>Scriptures</hi> by the Verbes <hi>active,</hi> and <hi>paſsive,</hi> to
<hi>ſcandalize,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 15 17, 18.</note> and to be
<hi>ſcandalized.</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 11.15, 24.</note> Active <hi>ſcandall</hi> is defined by <hi>Divines</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">S. Thom. 21.2. e. q. 43. ar. 1. S.
<hi>Hierom</hi> in c. 15. Matth.</note> out of Saint <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome,</hi> to be <hi>a word, or deed leſſe right,</hi> or leſſe good, <hi>giving occaſion to another of</hi> ſpirituall
<hi>ruine,</hi> or fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into ſinne. Neither doe they take the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe <hi>[leſſe]</hi> comparatively, but negatively,<note n="p" place="margin">S. Thom. above cited. <hi>Abulenſis</hi> in c. 18. Mat. 9.43.</note> for that which is <hi>not good,</hi> to wit, which <hi>hîc &amp; nunc</hi> in regard of ſome particular circumſtance of time, place, or perſons wanteth ſome
<hi>morall</hi> recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, or goodneſſe. <hi>Paſsive</hi> ſcandall, to wit, when one by the good, or bad word, or deede of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:4449:34"/>taketh occaſion to ſinne, or to be <hi>ſcandalized,</hi> is alſo of
<hi>two</hi> ſorts. For if one be <hi>ſcandalized</hi> through <hi>malice,</hi> it is called a
<hi>Scandall</hi> of the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,</hi> and is not to be regarded, according to that of our
<hi>Saviour,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Matth. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Let them alone, Blind they are</hi> &amp;c. But if one be <hi>ſcandalized</hi> through <hi>infirmity,</hi> or <hi>ignorance,</hi> it is called a <hi>Scandall</hi> of the <hi>weake,</hi> or <hi>little ones,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S.
<hi>Hierom</hi> in c. 15. Matth.</note> for <hi>the perfect,</hi> as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith, <hi>are not ſcandalized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="33">33 From whence the <hi>Divines</hi> with S. <hi>Thomas</hi> doe inferre, <hi>firſt</hi> that ſometimes <hi>paſsive</hi> ſcandall may be without <hi>active,</hi> as it was in the
<hi>ſcandall</hi> of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> or when one by the good word, or deed of another, eſpecially which is <hi>neceſſarie,</hi> and <hi>commanded,</hi> is <hi>ſcandalized,</hi> and taketh occaſion to ſinne thereby. Sometimes <hi>active</hi> ſcandall may bee without
<hi>paſsive,</hi> as when one by his bad word or deed, and ill example doth
<hi>ſcandalize,</hi> and giveth occaſion to others of falling into ſinne, and yet none is
<hi>ſcandalized,</hi> or taketh occaſion to ſinne thereby. And ſometimes they may bee both together, as when one by his bad example <hi>giveth,</hi> and another <hi>taketh</hi> occaſion to ſinne thereby. <hi>Secondly,</hi> they inferre, that no <hi>good workes,</hi> which are
<hi>neceſſary,</hi> as is the obſerving of <hi>precepts,</hi> can give occaſion of ſinning to any man, or, which is all one, can <hi>ſcandalize,</hi> or be an <hi>active</hi> ſcandall; neither are ſuch good workes to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to avoid the <hi>paſsive</hi> ſcandall even of the <hi>weake ones,</hi> as that moſt learned, and holy Biſhop
<hi>Alponſus Tostatus,</hi> for his admirable memorie,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:4449:34"/>and ſingular learning called <hi>the wonder of the world,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">See <hi>Bellarm.</hi> de Script. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. and Poſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin. in verbo <hi>Alphonſ. Tosta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi>
               </note> doth well obſerve, whoſe expreſſe words I thinke it not amiſſe heere to ſet downe.</p>
            <p n="34">34 <hi>For to omit</hi> (ſaith he)<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Abulenſis</hi> in cap. 18. Matth. <hi>q.</hi> 51.</note> 
               <hi>ſuch workes, which are of neceſsity, and commanded, were to ſinne mortally, and for no cauſe ought any man to ſinne mortally. But if they be</hi> Counſels, <hi>it is not of neceſsity to doe them. Yet ſometimes</hi> Counſels <hi>are made neceſſary, either in regard of the</hi> perſons <hi>as of thoſe, who have vowed the ſtate of perfection, or of thoſe, to whom by their ſtate perfection belongeth, or in regard of</hi> time, <hi>or</hi> place <hi>are alſo neceſſary for every man, as to give alms to him who is in extreme neceſsity. And ſo</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels <hi>are made to them</hi> precepts, <hi>to wit, that they are not to be omitted for any</hi> Scandal, <hi>as a</hi> religions <hi>man may not omit the obſerving of</hi> poverty, <hi>and</hi> chaſtity <hi>for any</hi> ſcandall. <hi>But when</hi> Counſels <hi>remaine in the nature of</hi> Counſels, <hi>that is, when the obſerving of them is not</hi> neceſſarie, <hi>then the</hi> ſcandall, <hi>which ariſeth to ſome by this, that others obſerve theſe</hi> Counſels, <hi>either proceedeth from</hi> malice, <hi>and then it is a</hi> ſcandall <hi>of the</hi> Phariſees, <hi>which is to be contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, neither is any ſpirituall good even not</hi> neceſſarie, <hi>to be omitted for this</hi> ſcandall. <hi>Or it proceedeth from</hi> infirmity <hi>or</hi> ignorance, <hi>and is called a</hi> ſcandall <hi>of the</hi> weake ones <hi>according to</hi> Saint Bernard,
<hi>becauſe it belongeth to</hi> weake ones <hi>to be</hi> ignorant, <hi>and moved through</hi> weakeneſſe, <hi>of which</hi> ſcandall <hi>it is ſaid Matth.</hi> 17. <hi>But that we may not ſcandalize them, goe to the Sea</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And for this</hi> ſcandall, <hi>we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine for a time from the workes of</hi> Counſels, <hi>or we
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:4449:35"/>muſt doe them ſecretly, leaſt the</hi> ignorant, <hi>whoſe mind is</hi> weake, <hi>be troubled, and this muſt be done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till having yeelded a reaſon of the workes of</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, <hi>and ſhewed that they are good, the</hi> ſcandall <hi>ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, which proceeded from</hi> ignorance. <hi>But if after a reaſon be yeeled, the</hi> ſcandall
<hi>ſhall not ceaſe, it is not to be called a</hi> ſcandall <hi>proceeding from</hi> igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, <hi>but from</hi> malice, <hi>and to be contemned, neither ought we to refraine from any good actions to avoid this ſcandall.</hi> Thus <hi>Abulenſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="35">35 The like hath <hi>Salmeron,</hi> and <hi>Estius:</hi> but <hi>Salmeron</hi> moreover addeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Salmeron</hi> tom. <hi>v.</hi> trac. 29.</note> that <hi>if the Doctrine, or action, which ſcandalizeth, be not neceſſary, but very profitable, and commodious, we muſt yeeld ſomething to the weakeneſſe of the</hi> little ones. <hi>But if the great ones</hi> [ſuch as are Prieſts, and Teachers] <hi>take this ſcandall, and the Doctrine, or action be profitable, they are not to be regarded, for they are incurable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are blinde, that is, they will not ſee, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, what God inſpireth in them</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>he that is weake</hi> (ſaith <hi>Estius</hi>) <hi>may be ſufficiently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Estius</hi> in cap. 8. ad cor. 1. ver. 13</note> 
               <hi>and taught, that his brother doth well, and that he ought not to be offended by his fact. After which ſufficient, and full inſtruction, if he ſtill per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere in ſcandall, it will not be a ſcandall</hi> given, <hi>but</hi> received, <hi>becauſe it will not now proceed from</hi> weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>but from</hi> malice, <hi>as was the</hi> ſcandall <hi>of the</hi> Phariſees, <hi>which as our</hi> Saviour <hi>in the Goſpell tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, we ought not to regard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="36">36 And by this it is apparant, that to <hi>take</hi> the Oath, ſuppoſing it to be lawfull, and <hi>commanded</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:4449:35"/>by lawfull authority under great penalties, can be no <hi>ſcandall</hi> to any man, ſeeing that the obſerving of lawfull <hi>precepts</hi> cannot give either to <hi>great ones,</hi> or to <hi>little ones</hi> any occaſion of <hi>ſpirituall</hi> ruine; neither ought we for any <hi>ſcandall</hi> even of the <hi>weake ones,</hi> omit the obſerving of ſuch
<hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts.</hi> But rather to <hi>refuſe</hi> the Oath, and to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the lawfull
<hi>practiſe</hi> of the <hi>Popes</hi> power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>Princes,</hi> which is the maine point denied therein, is very <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> and giveth over ample occaſion both to
<hi>Princes,</hi> and <hi>Subjects</hi> of manifold offence, and ruine, as I will ſhew beneath.<note n="t" place="margin">num. 44.</note> And therefore all thoſe who pretend the
<hi>taking</hi> of the Oath to be <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> doe ſuppoſe, but not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently prove (neither alſo doe they agree in their proofes) that it is altogether unlawfull, nor can be taken without danger at the leaſt of <hi>Perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> if not without a flat deniall of
<hi>Catholike faith,</hi> which how untrue it is, I have ſhewed above by expounding every Clauſe thereof in a true, and <hi>Catholike</hi> ſenſe.</p>
            <p n="37">37 Neither is it to the purpoſe, that many <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable</hi> arguments may be brought to prove, the <hi>Oath</hi> to be unlawfull, and conſequently to have in it a <hi>probable</hi> ſhew, and appearance of <hi>evill,</hi> from which the <hi>Apostle</hi> for the avoiding of
<hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall</hi> warneth us to refraine, <hi>from all ſhew of evill</hi> (ſaith he<note n="u" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.</note>) <hi>refraine your ſelves.</hi> For in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner many <hi>probable</hi> arguments, and anſweres may be brought to prove the <hi>Oath</hi> to be lawfull, and to containe nothing beſides a profeſſion of true <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:4449:36"/>Allegiance, and ſo from theſe words of S. <hi>Paul</hi> unleſſe they bee rightly underſtood, wee might infer, <hi>firſt</hi> that we muſt refraine both from
<hi>taking,</hi> and alſo from <hi>not taking</hi> the Oath, which is impoſſible, becauſe as in <hi>taking</hi> it there is a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable</hi> ſhew of <hi>ſpirituall</hi> diſobedience againſt the <hi>Popes Holineſſe,</hi> ſo in <hi>not taking</hi> it there is a more <hi>probable</hi> ſhew of <hi>temporall</hi> diſloyalty againſt the <hi>Kings Majestie,</hi> who hath purpoſely commanded the <hi>taking</hi> thereof, <hi>to make a triall, how his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſtand affected towards him in point of their loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, and due obedience</hi> &amp;c.<note n="x" place="margin">See above nu. 3.</note> and <hi>ſecondly</hi> that no man may lawfully follow the <hi>more probable</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion againſt the <hi>leſſe probable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vaſquez <hi>1</hi>a. <hi>2</hi>ae disp. <hi>62.</hi>
               </note> if the <hi>more proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> be the <hi>leſſe ſecure</hi> (which as <hi>Vaſquez</hi> affirmeth, is againſt the common Doctrine of <hi>Divines</hi>) ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that in the <hi>more probable</hi> opinion, if it be the <hi>leſſe ſecure,</hi> there is a <hi>probable</hi> ſhew of evill. Yea, which is more,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vaſquez.</hi> ibid. cap 4. num. 4.</note> 
               <hi>it is now</hi> (ſaith <hi>Vaſquez</hi>) <hi>and hath been long ſince the common opinion in Schooles, that it is lawfull for a learned man to follow in practiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his owne opinion which he judgeth to be the</hi> more probable, <hi>the opinion of others, although their opinion be the</hi> leſſe ſafe, <hi>and alſo in his judgement the</hi> leſſe probable, <hi>ſo that it be not deſtitute of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and probability.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="38">38 Wherefore the words of the <hi>Apostle</hi> may be well underſtood any one of theſe <hi>three</hi> waies; <hi>Firſt,</hi> that to avoid <hi>ſcandall,</hi> we muſt
<hi>refraine from all ſhew of evill,</hi> if in refraining there bee alſo no ſhew of evill, otherwiſe they would bind
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:4449:36"/>us to that which is impoſſible, for to refraine, and not to refraine from the ſame thing implieth a contradiction. Or <hi>ſecondly,</hi> that to avoid
<hi>ſcandall</hi> we muſt <hi>refraine from all ſhew of evill,</hi> unleſſe that thing which hath in it a ſhew of evill, be <hi>comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> by the <hi>constitutive</hi> precept of a lawfull Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, which as I ſhewed above,<note n="y" place="margin">num.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6 30.</note> muſt be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo long as it is not <hi>manifestly</hi> unjuſt, nor in <hi>prejudice</hi> of a <hi>third</hi> perſon, neither is it ſufficient, that it hath onely a <hi>probable</hi> ſhew of evill. Or
<hi>thirdly,</hi> that to avoid the <hi>ſcandall</hi> of the <hi>weake ones,</hi> we muſt
<hi>refraine from all ſhew of evill,</hi> untill they be <hi>instructed,</hi> and admoniſhed, that although it ſeeme to them to be <hi>evill,</hi> and hath a ſhew of <hi>evill,</hi> yet in very deed it is not <hi>evill,</hi> but good. After which <hi>instruction,</hi> and admonition, if they ſtill perſiſt in their <hi>ſcandall,</hi> it is not a <hi>ſcandall</hi> of the
<hi>little ones,</hi> but of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and the <hi>great ones,</hi> neither doth it proceed from <hi>infirmity,</hi> or <hi>ignorance,</hi> but from <hi>malice,</hi> and is not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="observation">
            <head>The fift and last Obſervation.</head>
            <p n="39">39 <hi>FIftly,</hi> and laſtly, to know which is the <hi>ſafer,</hi> and the
<hi>leſſe ſafe</hi> way, part, or opinion, and how it is diſtinguiſhed from the
<hi>more,</hi> or <hi>leſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable</hi> and in what ſenſe that vulgar ſaying, <hi>The ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer way is to be choſen,</hi> is to be underſtood, we muſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:4449:37"/>obſerve <hi>firſt</hi> of all, that the <hi>ſafer,</hi> and the
<hi>leſſe ſafe,</hi> may either be taken <hi>comparatively,</hi> as the <hi>more,</hi> and
<hi>leſſe probable</hi> are alwaies ſo taken, and ſo the <hi>leſſe ſafe</hi> is ever
<hi>ſafe,</hi> although not <hi>ſo ſafe,</hi> as is the other to which it is compared, as every Nowne <hi>comparative</hi> being taken <hi>comparatively,</hi> doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies include the
<hi>poſitive.</hi> And in this ſenſe that vulgar ſaying is not to be underſtood, becauſe it is ſufficient to follow that which is <hi>ſafe,</hi> neither are we bound to chooſe alwaies the <hi>ſafer,</hi> ſo that the <hi>leſſe ſafe</hi> be <hi>ſafe</hi> enough: <hi>Or elſe</hi> it may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>negatively,</hi> for that which is <hi>not ſafe,</hi> as the Adverbe <hi>[leſſe]</hi> was taken above<note n="z" place="margin">num.
32.</note> in the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Scandall,</hi> and in this ſenſe the <hi>leſſe ſafe</hi> way, part, or opinion is never to bee choſen, but wee muſt alwaies chooſe that, which is at the leaſt wiſe <hi>ſafe.</hi> But to know how the <hi>Divines</hi> doe commonly take the <hi>ſafer,</hi> and the <hi>leſſe ſafe,</hi> and do diſtinguiſh them from the
<hi>more,</hi> and <hi>leſſe probable,</hi> I thinke it not amiſſe, to relate here
<hi>verbatim</hi> what <hi>Vaſquez</hi> write<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h of this point.</p>
            <p n="40">40 Among opinions (<hi>ſaith he</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vaſquez</hi>
1<hi>a.</hi> 2<hi>ae.</hi> diſp 62. c. 1 num. 1.</note>) the one is <hi>ſafer,</hi> the other
<hi>leſſe ſafe,</hi> it is called the <hi>more ſafe,</hi> not becauſe it is the <hi>more probable, but becauſe</hi> he that followeth it cannot ſinne. <hi>As if there be</hi> two contrarie opinions concerning <hi>reſtitution, that</hi> which ſaith that ſome thing is to bee <hi>reſtored,</hi> is called the <hi>ſafer,</hi> becauſe in <hi>restoring</hi> there can be no ſin, and the contrary is the <hi>leſſe ſafe,</hi> becauſe in <hi>not reſtoring</hi> there may be ſin, and ſo of other matters. <hi>In like manner</hi> the more
<hi>ſafe</hi> part (ſaith
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:4449:37"/>
               <hi>Vaſquez</hi>) is to be accounted that,<note place="margin">Vaſquez
<hi>1</hi>a. <hi>2</hi>ae. diſp. <hi>66.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi> num. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> wherein there would be the <hi>leſſer</hi> ſin than in the contrary, when it is neceſſary to chooſe one of thoſe two, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is ſin. For when ſoever two evils meet ſo together, that it is neceſſary to chuſe one of them, <hi>that</hi> doubtleſſe is to be choſen, which otherwiſe would be the <hi>leſſer,</hi> and conſequently in chooſing that there can be no ſinne at all. And the reaſon is manifeſt; for ſeeing that in no caſe it muſt be granted, that any man of neceſſitie bee ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed, but that he may chuſe the one part with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſin, and that if of <hi>two evills</hi> the one of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity muſt be choſen, there is greater reaſon, that we ſhould chuſe the <hi>leſſer,</hi> it followeth, that the <hi>leſſer</hi> may be choſen without ſin, and ſo that, which abſolutely conſidered by it ſelfe would be evill, is then no ſinne, when it occurreth with a greater evill. An example hereof <hi>Vaſquez</hi> bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and examineth at large of one, who after he is <hi>married,</hi> doubteth of ſome impediment, which annulleth the
<hi>Marriage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="41">41 Moreover <hi>among opinions</hi> (ſaith <hi>Vaſquez</hi>) <hi>one is the</hi> more probable,<note place="margin">Vaſquez disp. <hi>62.</hi> cap <hi>1.</hi> nu. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>the other is</hi> leſſe proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>The</hi> more probable <hi>is that, which hath the better grounds, and the</hi> leſſe probable, <hi>which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it hath not better grounds, yet the grounds thereof want not ſufficient probability. It may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fall out, that the</hi> leſſe ſafe <hi>opinion be the</hi> more probable, <hi>that is, that part wherein perchance there may be ſinne, to be the</hi> more probable, <hi>and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe that part, wherein there can be no ſinne, to be
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:4449:38"/>the</hi> leſſe probable. <hi>As in the example of making</hi> reſtitution, <hi>that part which ſaith, that we ought not to</hi> reſtore, <hi>may be the</hi> more probable, <hi>and contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that part which ſaith, that wee must</hi> reſtore, <hi>may have farre weaker grounds, yea, and ſometimes it may have no probabilitie,</hi> or probable grounds <hi>at all.</hi> Thus <hi>Vaſquez.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="42">42 And from hence it may be eaſily gathered <hi>firſt,</hi> that the <hi>more,</hi> or <hi>leſſe probable</hi> opinion (which are taken here <hi>comparatively,</hi> and ſuppoſe both opinions to be truly <hi>probable</hi>) may be grounded either upon
<hi>intrinſecall principles</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">See <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſquez diſp.</hi> 62. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi>
10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>, as are <hi>cauſes, effects, abſurdities,</hi> or other like arguments, which ſhew the opinion to be in it ſelfe <hi>truer</hi> than the contrary, of which ſort of
<hi>principles,</hi> unleſſe they be very cleare, and eaſie to be underſtood, onely the
<hi>learned</hi> are able to judge, or upon <hi>extriaſecall,</hi> and which the
<hi>unlearned</hi> may eaſily underſtand, to wit, the authority of learned men, who are skilfull in that opinion which they approve, and that if perchance they be miſtaken in the grounds of their opinion, and that their reaſons be not true but falſe, their authority, and approving of that opinion cannot make it truly <hi>probable</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Vaſquez diſp. <hi>62.</hi> &amp; cap. <hi>4.</hi> paragr. Obſervandum temen maximè.</note> to thoſe, who ſee the manifeſt falſhood of their
<hi>principles,</hi> But how farre forth either the learned, or unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, who not conſidering the <hi>falſhood</hi> of their reaſons, and <hi>principles</hi> doe approve, and follow in practiſe their opinion, may be excuſed in <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> I will not judge, but leave their <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> to themſelves, and to the judgement of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:4449:38"/>GOD, who onely ſearcheth the ſecrets of all mens hearts.</p>
            <p n="43">43 <hi>Secondly,</hi> that when <hi>Divines</hi> affirme, <hi>The ſafer part</hi> is alwayes to be choſen: by the <hi>ſafer</hi> they underſtand that, which is without
<hi>ſinne,</hi> or <hi>danger</hi> of ſinne; for to expoſe ones ſelfe to <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> of ſinning, is alwayes accounted a ſin, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that, <hi>Who loveth danger, ſhall periſh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.</note>: and by the <hi>leſſe ſafe,</hi> they underſtand that which is <hi>not ſafe,</hi> becauſe it cannot be choſen lawfully, and without <hi>danger</hi> of ſinne, for ſafe is accounted that, which is without all <hi>danger.</hi> And in this ſenſe every opinion, which is truly <hi>proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> is a
<hi>ſafe</hi> opinion, becauſe it may be followed <hi>lawfully,</hi> and therefore
<hi>ſafely,</hi> that is, without ſin, or <hi>danger</hi> of ſinne. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that this <hi>Maxime</hi> of the <hi>Canon</hi> Law<note n="e" place="margin">Cap. Ad au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientiam, &amp;c. Significaſti, <hi>1.</hi> el <hi>2.</hi> de homicidio<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; cap. Iuvenis de S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> onſalibit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>In doubts the ſafer part is to bee choſen;</hi> is not to be underſtood of <hi>doubts</hi> as <hi>doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> is taken ſometimes for <hi>probable,</hi> uncertaine, or <hi>queſtionable,</hi> but of ſuch <hi>doubts,</hi> which leave the underſtanding ſo perplexed, and in ſuſpence, that it giveth no determinate, or probable aſſent to either part of the queſtion, to wit, whether the thing which is <hi>doubted</hi> of, be true, or falſe, law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, or unlawful, for this is properly to be <hi>doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi> and nevertheleſſe how in theſe <hi>doubts</hi> the <hi>conſtitutive</hi> precept of a lawfull Superiour, and whoſe authoritie is not queſtionable, if it be not in prejudice of a
<hi>third</hi> perſon, ought to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed, and how the <hi>Subject,</hi> who ſo
<hi>doubteth,</hi> whether the thing which is commanded be juſt,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:4449:39"/>or unjuſt, may, notwithſtanding this <hi>doubt,</hi> frame his conſcience rightly to obey his <hi>Superiours</hi> commandement,<note place="margin">Vaſquez <hi>1</hi>a.
<hi>2</hi>ae. disp. <hi>65.</hi> &amp; <hi>65.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vaſquez,</hi> and other
<hi>Divines,</hi> who treat of a <hi>doubtfull</hi> conſcience, as it is diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from a <hi>probable,</hi> doe at large declare.</p>
            <p n="44">44 <hi>Fourthly,</hi> that ſuppoſing <hi>firſt,</hi> that no one <hi>Clauſe</hi> of the <hi>Oath</hi> can be clearely convinced to be unlawfull (for to heape up together never ſo many <hi>probable</hi> arguments againſt it were to no purpoſe) and conſequently that the
<hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> in framing, and commanding it, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed a <hi>probable</hi> opinion: <hi>ſecondly,</hi> that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Subject is bound to obey the <hi>conſtitutive</hi> precept of his lawfull <hi>Superiour,</hi> when hee commandeth according to a <hi>probable</hi> opinion (for, as I ſaid above<note n="e" place="margin">num. 26.27.</note>, there is not the ſame reaſon of a <hi>declarative</hi>) and <hi>thirdly,</hi> that the <hi>Popes Breves</hi> forbidding the <hi>Oath,</hi> are <hi>declarative,</hi> and groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon <hi>falſe</hi> reaſons, and ſuppoſitions, it is not onely the <hi>ſafer</hi> way to <hi>take</hi> the <hi>Oath,</hi> than to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe</hi> it, but alſo in <hi>refuſing</hi> it there is no <hi>ſafety</hi> at all, if we duely conſider the manifold <hi>dangers,</hi> and <hi>ſcandals,</hi> which do ariſe by <hi>refuſing</hi> it, and by <hi>covertly</hi> approving the damnable
<hi>practice</hi> of the <hi>Popes Power</hi> to depoſe <hi>Princes,</hi> which is the onely point denied therein, and for which it was pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely deviſed, and under great penalties ſo ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commanded. All which <hi>dangers,</hi> and <hi>ſcandals,</hi> the moſt learned
<hi>Sorbon</hi> Doctors in their <hi>cenſure</hi> of <hi>Santarellus</hi> doctrine (which teacheth, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath power <hi>to puniſh Kings, and Princes with
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:4449:39"/>temporall puniſhments, depoſe and deprive them of their Kingdomes for hereſie, and to diſcharge their Subjects from their obedience,</hi> &amp;c.) doe fully, though briefly relate, by condemning the ſaid
<q>
                  <hi>doctrine,</hi> and the <hi>ſequels</hi> thereof, <hi>as new, falſe, erroneous, contrary to the Word of</hi> GOD; <hi>making the Pontificall Dignitie to be odious, opening the way to Schiſme; derogating from the ſupreme au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Kings, which dependeth upon</hi> GOD
<hi>alone; hindering the converſion of Infidell, and hereticall Princes; disturbing the publike peace, overthrowing Kingdomes, States, and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths; withdrawing Subjects from their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſubjection, and ſtirring them up to facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, rebellions, ſeditions, and murthering of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Given in the Sorbon the first, and reviewed the fourth of Aprill,</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">See above, num. 7.</note> 1626.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="45">45 <hi>Laſtly,</hi> that the <hi>example</hi> of one, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dangerouſly
<hi>ſicke,</hi> ought in wiſdome <hi>to chooſe that Phyſicke, which is the more ſafe, the more aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the more probable,</hi> is no fit <hi>example</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade any man not to take the <hi>Oath: First,</hi> for that no man ought in wiſdome for the cure of his bodie to ſeeke after the learnedſt <hi>Phyſitians,</hi> and chooſe the <hi>most ſafe,</hi> and the <hi>most probable</hi> Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, whereby he ſhall conſume his whole eſtate, and bring himſelfe, his wife, and children to beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery; but he ought in wiſdome to content him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with ſuch <hi>Phyſitians,</hi> and <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> which one, two, or three learned
<hi>Phyſitians</hi> without ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after the learnedſt of all, ſhall with mature
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:4449:40"/>adviſe, and conſultation thinke will cure his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe.
<hi>Secondly,</hi> for that this <hi>example</hi> if it be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the <hi>Oath,</hi> and to the cure of the <hi>ſoule,</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth <hi>firſt,</hi> that whoſoever taketh the
<hi>Oath,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing commanded by the <hi>constitutive</hi> precept of his Soveraigne
<hi>Prince,</hi> is in <hi>danger</hi> of his <hi>ſoule,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hee follow therein a
<hi>probable</hi> opinion, which how untrue it is I have ſhewed above<note n="g" place="margin">num. 26.</note>. <hi>Secondly,</hi> that to follow a <hi>probable</hi> opinion againſt the <hi>more probable,</hi> is dangerous to ones ſoule, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though by not following it hee ſhall incurre a <hi>Praemunire,</hi> which to affirme were <hi>certes</hi> rather a great
<hi>folly,</hi> than <hi>wiſdome,</hi> and a farre greater <hi>folly</hi> to go about to perſwade any <hi>wiſe</hi> man to beleeve the ſame<note n="h" place="margin">See above, num.
37.</note>. And <hi>thirdly,</hi> that to <hi>refuſe</hi> the <hi>Oath</hi> is the <hi>more ſafe,</hi> and the <hi>more probable</hi> opinion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is diſproved by the
<hi>Popes</hi> Holineſſe, and the greater number of <hi>Catholike Divines,</hi> who follow his opinion; whereas the approving, or diſproving of the <hi>Pope,</hi> or other <hi>Doctors,</hi> cannot make their opinion to be the <hi>more probable,</hi> yea, or <hi>probable</hi> at all, and ſo <hi>not ſafe</hi> to thoſe, who ſee their approving, or diſproving to be grounded upon
<hi>falſe</hi> reaſons, and ſuppoſitions<note n="i" place="margin">See above, num.
14.</note>, as are the <hi>Popes</hi> declarative <hi>Breves</hi> forbidding the <hi>Oath,</hi> as I have ſhewed above<note n="k" place="margin">num. 59.</note>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:4449:40"/>
            <head>The Concluſion.</head>
            <p n="46">46 NOw to make an end, theſe <hi>five Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and the former
<hi>Explications</hi> of the <hi>Oath</hi> (which I have not invented of my ſelfe, but onely abſtracted them out of thoſe <hi>Authours,</hi> who have written of this Subject more exactly) ſeeme to my underſtanding ſo cleare and convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, that I have thought good to recommend them to the ſerious conſiderations of all Engliſh <hi>Roman</hi> Catholikes, thoſe eſpecially who have taken upon them the charge of ſoules, and in that regard are bound to inſtruct the unlearneder ſort of people both men, and women in their dutie to <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Caeſar,</hi> and to teach them truely, ſincerely and without any inordinate reſpect of
<hi>humane</hi> feare, or favour, what <hi>ſpirituall</hi> obedience they owe to the <hi>Popes Holineſſe,</hi> and what <hi>temporall</hi> to the <hi>Kings Majestie,</hi> and have not perchance hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to examined this great, and important controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of the <hi>Oath,</hi> betwixt the <hi>Pope,</hi> and their <hi>Prince</hi> ſo diligently, and uprightly, as they might, and in regard of their <hi>Paſtorall</hi> charge ought to have done; to the end that they may clearely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that thoſe their <hi>Catholike</hi> brethren, who out of conſcience, and obedience to their <hi>Soveraigne</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:4449:41"/>have taken the <hi>Oath,</hi> thinking it their dutie ſo to doe, and have thereby according to his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement acknowledged that <hi>temporall</hi> Allegiance, which according to the grounds of <hi>Catholik</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is due to our ſupreme <hi>temporall</hi> Prince, have no waies departed from the bond of that true <hi>ſpirituall</hi> obedience, which is due to our ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme <hi>ſpirituall</hi> Paſtour. In all which if I have any way not wittingly, or willingly, I call <hi>God</hi> to witneſſe, erred through ignorance, I moſt humbly ſubmit my ſelfe to the iudgement, and Cenſure of the holy <hi>Catholike, Apostolike Roman</hi> Church, and would alſo have beene willing for peace, and obedience ſake, to have lead captive, and blind-fold my will, contrary to my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, to the obſerving of his
<hi>Holineſſe Breves,</hi> if they had concerned a <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> and not a
<hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall</hi> matter, and alſo in his owne cauſe, to the great <hi>prejudice,</hi> and againſt the expreſſe <hi>commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of our <hi>Soveraigne Prince,</hi> by challenging ſince the time of Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh (A <hi>thing unheard of before that age</hi> (ſaith <hi>Onuphrius</hi>) <hi>in competent attributes</hi> (as a learned
<hi>Catholike</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them<note n="l" place="margin">See the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie</hi> for the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church in the <hi>Preface ſec.</hi> 20.</note>) of <hi>ſupreme authority,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Onuphrius <hi>lib. 4</hi> de varia creat. Rom. Pont.</note>
               <hi>and principallity in temporalls</hi> over all the <hi>Chriſtian Monarches</hi> of the world, to <hi>diſpoſe</hi> of their <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> and <hi>Dominions</hi> at leaſt wiſe
<hi>indirectly</hi> or in order to <hi>ſpirituall</hi> good, with imminen danger of the
<hi>ſpirituall</hi> and temporall ruine of all. <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, and manifeſt overthrow of the <hi>temporall</hi> Soveraigntie of the <hi>Kings Majeſtie,</hi> and of all
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:4449:41"/>other <hi>Soveraigne Princes,</hi> whom the ancient <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> with uniforme conſent,<note n="m" place="margin">S. Ignatius in epiſt. ad Smyr. Irenaeus lib.
<hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>24.</hi> Tertul. in Apolog c <hi>33.</hi> &amp; ad S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam Clem A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex lib <hi>4</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>24</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>50.</hi> Optatus M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>levit lib. <hi>3.</hi> contra Parmenian. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egor, N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. in
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>27.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſo. Ambroſ. in Apologia <hi>David,</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>2</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. <hi>7.</hi> &amp;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> de ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſii. Hieronymus epiſt
<hi>22.</hi> ad Euſtechium, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>36.</hi> ad Ruſticum. Chryſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m. <hi>2</hi> &amp;
<hi>20</hi> ad pop. Antioch. &amp; ad Rom. <hi>13.</hi> Aug de fide &amp; epe. ib cap. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8.</hi> conc. <hi>31</hi> &amp; tract. <hi>115.</hi> in Ioan. Cyril. Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x lib <hi>12</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ioan cap. <hi>56.</hi> Greg
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>g. lib. <hi>2.</hi> epiſt. <hi>61.</hi> Iſid lib. <hi>3.</hi> ſent. cap. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rd. epiſt. <hi>42.</hi> ad
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>chiep. Senon. Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a, Euthym. Arnob. Caſſiod. in illud Pſal. <hi>50.</hi> Tibi ſoli pecca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Theod. Theophyl. Occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. ad Rom. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> acknowledge to be <hi>ſupreme</hi> in temporals, and ſubject to the
<hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall</hi> puniſhment of none but of GOD <hi>alone;</hi> and that to deprive
<hi>Princes</hi> of their <hi>temporall Kingdomes, Dominions,</hi> or <hi>Lives,</hi> for what cauſe, crime, or end ſoever <hi>temporall,</hi> or <hi>ſpirituall, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly,</hi> or
<hi>indirectly</hi> they be deprived, is a <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall puniſhment;</hi> I thinke no man that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>d with naturall reaſon can deny.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
